<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. A lane by the wall of Capulet's orchard.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter ROMEO</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Can I go forward when my heart is here?</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">Turn back, dull earth, and find thy centre out.</a><br/>
<p><i>He climbs the wall, and leaps down within it</i></p>
<p><i>Enter BENVOLIO and MERCUTIO</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>BENVOLIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="3">Romeo! my cousin Romeo!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="4">He is wise;</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">And, on my lie, hath stol'n him home to bed.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>BENVOLIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="6">He ran this way, and leap'd this orchard wall:</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Call, good Mercutio.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="8">Nay, I'll conjure too.</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Romeo! humours! madman! passion! lover!</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">Appear thou in the likeness of a sigh:</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Speak but one rhyme, and I am satisfied;</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">Cry but 'Ay me!' pronounce but 'love' and 'dove;'</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">Speak to my gossip Venus one fair word,</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">One nick-name for her purblind son and heir,</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">Young Adam Cupid, he that shot so trim,</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">When King Cophetua loved the beggar-maid!</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">He heareth not, he stirreth not, he moveth not;</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">The ape is dead, and I must conjure him.</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">I conjure thee by Rosaline's bright eyes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">By her high forehead and her scarlet lip,</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">By her fine foot, straight leg and quivering thigh</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">And the demesnes that there adjacent lie,</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">That in thy likeness thou appear to us!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>BENVOLIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="24">And if he hear thee, thou wilt anger him.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="25">This cannot anger him: 'twould anger him</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">To raise a spirit in his mistress' circle</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">Of some strange nature, letting it there stand</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">Till she had laid it and conjured it down;</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">That were some spite: my invocation</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Is fair and honest, and in his mistres s' name</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">I conjure only but to raise up him.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>BENVOLIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="32">Come, he hath hid himself among these trees,</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">To be consorted with the humorous night:</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">Blind is his love and best befits the dark.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="35">If love be blind, love cannot hit the mark.</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">Now will he sit under a medlar tree,</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">And wish his mistress were that kind of fruit</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">As maids call medlars, when they laugh alone.</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">Romeo, that she were, O, that she were</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">An open et caetera, thou a poperin pear!</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">Romeo, good night: I'll to my truckle-bed;</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">This field-bed is too cold for me to sleep:</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">Come, shall we go?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>BENVOLIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="44">                  Go, then; for 'tis in vain</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">To seek him here that means not to be found.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
