<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE V. Capulet's orchard.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter JULIET</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">The clock struck nine when I did send the nurse;</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">In half an hour she promised to return.</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">Perchance she cannot meet him: that's not so.</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">O, she is lame! love's heralds should be thoughts,</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Which ten times faster glide than the sun's beams,</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">Driving back shadows over louring hills:</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Therefore do nimble-pinion'd doves draw love,</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">And therefore hath the wind-swift Cupid wings.</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Now is the sun upon the highmost hill</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">Of this day's journey, and from nine till twelve</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Is three long hours, yet she is not come.</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">Had she affections and warm youthful blood,</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">She would be as swift in motion as a ball;</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">My words would bandy her to my sweet love,</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">And his to me:</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">But old folks, many feign as they were dead;</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">Unwieldy, slow, heavy and pale as lead.</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">O God, she comes!</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter Nurse and PETER</i></p>
<a NAME="19">O honey nurse, what news?</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">Hast thou met with him? Send thy man away.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="21">Peter, stay at the gate.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit PETER</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="22">Now, good sweet nurse,--O Lord, why look'st thou sad?</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Though news be sad, yet tell them merrily;</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">If good, thou shamest the music of sweet news</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">By playing it to me with so sour a face.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="26">I am a-weary, give me leave awhile:</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">Fie, how my bones ache! what a jaunt have I had!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="28">I would thou hadst my bones, and I thy news:</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Nay, come, I pray thee, speak; good, good nurse, speak.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="30">Jesu, what haste? can you not stay awhile?</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">Do you not see that I am out of breath?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="32">How art thou out of breath, when thou hast breath</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">To say to me that thou art out of breath?</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">The excuse that thou dost make in this delay</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">Is longer than the tale thou dost excuse.</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">Is thy news good, or bad? answer to that;</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">Say either, and I'll stay the circumstance:</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">Let me be satisfied, is't good or bad?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="39">Well, you have made a simple choice; you know not</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">how to choose a man: Romeo! no, not he; though his</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">face be better than any man's, yet his leg excels</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">all men's; and for a hand, and a foot, and a body,</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">though they be not to be talked on, yet they are</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">past compare: he is not the flower of courtesy,</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">but, I'll warrant him, as gentle as a lamb. Go thy</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">ways, wench; serve God. What, have you dined at home?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="47">No, no: but all this did I know before.</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">What says he of our marriage? what of that?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="49">Lord, how my head aches! what a head have I!</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">It beats as it would fall in twenty pieces.</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">My back o' t' other side,--O, my back, my back!</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">Beshrew your heart for sending me about,</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">To catch my death with jaunting up and down!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="54">I' faith, I am sorry that thou art not well.</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">Sweet, sweet, sweet nurse, tell me, what says my love?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="56">Your love says, like an honest gentleman, and a</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">courteous, and a kind, and a handsome, and, I</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">warrant, a virtuous,--Where is your mother?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="59">Where is my mother! why, she is within;</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">Where should she be? How oddly thou repliest!</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">'Your love says, like an honest gentleman,</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">Where is your mother?'</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="63">O God's lady dear!</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">Are you so hot? marry, come up, I trow;</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">Is this the poultice for my aching bones?</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">Henceforward do your messages yourself.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="67">Here's such a coil! come, what says Romeo?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="68">Have you got leave to go to shrift to-day?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="69">I have.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="70">Then hie you hence to Friar Laurence' cell;</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">There stays a husband to make you a wife:</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">Now comes the wanton blood up in your cheeks,</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">They'll be in scarlet straight at any news.</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">Hie you to church; I must another way,</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">To fetch a ladder, by the which your love</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">Must climb a bird's nest soon when it is dark:</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">I am the drudge and toil in your delight,</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">But you shall bear the burden soon at night.</a><br/>
<a NAME="79">Go; I'll to dinner: hie you to the cell.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="80">Hie to high fortune! Honest nurse, farewell.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
