<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE IV. A street.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter ROMEO, MERCUTIO, BENVOLIO, with five or six Maskers, Torch-bearers, and others</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">What, shall this speech be spoke for our excuse?</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">Or shall we on without a apology?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>BENVOLIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="3">The date is out of such prolixity:</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">We'll have no Cupid hoodwink'd with a scarf,</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Bearing a Tartar's painted bow of lath,</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">Scaring the ladies like a crow-keeper;</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Nor no without-book prologue, faintly spoke</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">After the prompter, for our entrance:</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">But let them measure us by what they will;</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">We'll measure them a measure, and be gone.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="11">Give me a torch: I am not for this ambling;</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">Being but heavy, I will bear the light.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="13">Nay, gentle Romeo, we must have you dance.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="14">Not I, believe me: you have dancing shoes</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">With nimble soles: I have a soul of lead</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">So stakes me to the ground I cannot move.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="17">You are a lover; borrow Cupid's wings,</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">And soar with them above a common bound.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="19">I am too sore enpierced with his shaft</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">To soar with his light feathers, and so bound,</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">I cannot bound a pitch above dull woe:</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">Under love's heavy burden do I sink.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="23">And, to sink in it, should you burden love;</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">Too great oppression for a tender thing.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="25">Is love a tender thing? it is too rough,</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">Too rude, too boisterous, and it pricks like thorn.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="27">If love be rough with you, be rough with love;</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">Prick love for pricking, and you beat love down.</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Give me a case to put my visage in:</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">A visor for a visor! what care I</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">What curious eye doth quote deformities?</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">Here are the beetle brows shall blush for me.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>BENVOLIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="33">Come, knock and enter; and no sooner in,</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">But every man betake him to his legs.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="35">A torch for me: let wantons light of heart</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">Tickle the senseless rushes with their heels,</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">For I am proverb'd with a grandsire phrase;</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">I'll be a candle-holder, and look on.</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">The game was ne'er so fair, and I am done.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="40">Tut, dun's the mouse, the constable's own word:</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">If thou art dun, we'll draw thee from the mire</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">Of this sir-reverence love, wherein thou stick'st</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">Up to the ears. Come, we burn daylight, ho!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="44">Nay, that's not so.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="45">I mean, sir, in delay</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">We waste our lights in vain, like lamps by day.</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">Take our good meaning, for our judgment sits</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">Five times in that ere once in our five wits.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="49">And we mean well in going to this mask;</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">But 'tis no wit to go.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="51">Why, may one ask?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="52">I dream'd a dream to-night.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="53">And so did I.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="54">Well, what was yours?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="55">That dreamers often lie.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="56">In bed asleep, while they do dream things true.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="57">O, then, I see Queen Mab hath been with you.</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">She is the fairies' midwife, and she comes</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">In shape no bigger than an agate-stone</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">On the fore-finger of an alderman,</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">Drawn with a team of little atomies</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">Athwart men's noses as they lie asleep;</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">Her wagon-spokes made of long spiders' legs,</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">The cover of the wings of grasshoppers,</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">The traces of the smallest spider's web,</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">The collars of the moonshine's watery beams,</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">Her whip of cricket's bone, the lash of film,</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">Her wagoner a small grey-coated gnat,</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">Not so big as a round little worm</a><br/>
<a NAME="70">Prick'd from the lazy finger of a maid;</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">Her chariot is an empty hazel-nut</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">Made by the joiner squirrel or old grub,</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">Time out o' mind the fairies' coachmakers.</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">And in this state she gallops night by night</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">Through lovers' brains, and then they dream of love;</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">O'er courtiers' knees, that dream on court'sies straight,</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">O'er lawyers' fingers, who straight dream on fees,</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">O'er ladies ' lips, who straight on kisses dream,</a><br/>
<a NAME="79">Which oft the angry Mab with blisters plagues,</a><br/>
<a NAME="80">Because their breaths with sweetmeats tainted are:</a><br/>
<a NAME="81">Sometime she gallops o'er a courtier's nose,</a><br/>
<a NAME="82">And then dreams he of smelling out a suit;</a><br/>
<a NAME="83">And sometime comes she with a tithe-pig's tail</a><br/>
<a NAME="84">Tickling a parson's nose as a' lies asleep,</a><br/>
<a NAME="85">Then dreams, he of another benefice:</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">Sometime she driveth o'er a soldier's neck,</a><br/>
<a NAME="87">And then dreams he of cutting foreign throats,</a><br/>
<a NAME="88">Of breaches, ambuscadoes, Spanish blades,</a><br/>
<a NAME="89">Of healths five-fathom deep; and then anon</a><br/>
<a NAME="90">Drums in his ear, at which he starts and wakes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="91">And being thus frighted swears a prayer or two</a><br/>
<a NAME="92">And sleeps again. This is that very Mab</a><br/>
<a NAME="93">That plats the manes of horses in the night,</a><br/>
<a NAME="94">And bakes the elflocks in foul sluttish hairs,</a><br/>
<a NAME="95">Which once untangled, much misfortune bodes:</a><br/>
<a NAME="96">This is the hag, when maids lie on their backs,</a><br/>
<a NAME="97">That presses them and learns them first to bear,</a><br/>
<a NAME="98">Making them women of good carriage:</a><br/>
<a NAME="99">This is she--</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech24"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="100">                  Peace, peace, Mercutio, peace!</a><br/>
<a NAME="101">Thou talk'st of nothing.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech25"><b>MERCUTIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="102">True, I talk of dreams,</a><br/>
<a NAME="103">Which are the children of an idle brain,</a><br/>
<a NAME="104">Begot of nothing but vain fantasy,</a><br/>
<a NAME="105">Which is as thin of substance as the air</a><br/>
<a NAME="106">And more inconstant than the wind, who wooes</a><br/>
<a NAME="107">Even now the frozen bosom of the north,</a><br/>
<a NAME="108">And, being anger'd, puffs away from thence,</a><br/>
<a NAME="109">Turning his face to the dew-dropping south.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech26"><b>BENVOLIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="110">This wind, you talk of, blows us from ourselves;</a><br/>
<a NAME="111">Supper is done, and we shall come too late.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech27"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="112">I fear, too early: for my mind misgives</a><br/>
<a NAME="113">Some consequence yet hanging in the stars</a><br/>
<a NAME="114">Shall bitterly begin his fearful date</a><br/>
<a NAME="115">With this night's revels and expire the term</a><br/>
<a NAME="116">Of a despised life closed in my breast</a><br/>
<a NAME="117">By some vile forfeit of untimely death.</a><br/>
<a NAME="118">But He, that hath the steerage of my course,</a><br/>
<a NAME="119">Direct my sail! On, lusty gentlemen.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech28"><b>BENVOLIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="120">Strike, drum.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
