<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE III. Friar Laurence's cell.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter FRIAR LAURENCE</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Romeo, come forth; come forth, thou fearful man:</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">Affliction is enamour'd of thy parts,</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">And thou art wedded to calamity.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter ROMEO</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="4">Father, what news? what is the prince's doom?</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">What sorrow craves acquaintance at my hand,</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">That I yet know not?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="7">Too familiar</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">Is my dear son with such sour company:</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">I bring thee tidings of the prince's doom.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="10">What less than dooms-day is the prince's doom?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="11">A gentler judgment vanish'd from his lips,</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">Not body's death, but body's banishment.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="13">Ha, banishment! be merciful, say 'death;'</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">For exile hath more terror in his look,</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">Much more than death: do not say 'banishment.'</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="16">Hence from Verona art thou banished:</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">Be patient, for the world is broad and wide.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="18">There is no world without Verona walls,</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">But purgatory, torture, hell itself.</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">Hence-banished is banish'd from the world,</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">And world's exile is death: then banished,</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">Is death mis-term'd: calling death banishment,</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Thou cutt'st my head off with a golden axe,</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">And smilest upon the stroke that murders me.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="25">O deadly sin! O rude unthankfulness!</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">Thy fault our law calls death; but the kind prince,</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">Taking thy part, hath rush'd aside the law,</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">And turn'd that black word death to banishment:</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">This is dear mercy, and thou seest it not.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="30">'Tis torture, and not mercy: heaven is here,</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">Where Juliet lives; and every cat and dog</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">And little mouse, every unworthy thing,</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">Live here in heaven and may look on her;</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">But Romeo may not: more validity,</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">More honourable state, more courtship lives</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">In carrion-flies than Romeo: they my seize</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">On the white wonder of dear Juliet's hand</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">And steal immortal blessing from her lips,</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">Who even in pure and vestal modesty,</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">Still blush, as thinking their own kisses sin;</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">But Romeo may not; he is banished:</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">Flies may do this, but I from this must fly:</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">They are free men, but I am banished.</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">And say'st thou yet that exile is not death?</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">Hadst thou no poison mix'd, no sharp-ground knife,</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">No sudden mean of death, though ne'er so mean,</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">But 'banished' to kill me?--'banished'?</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">O friar, the damned use that word in hell;</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">Howlings attend it: how hast thou the heart,</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">Being a divine, a ghostly confessor,</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">A sin-absolver, and my friend profess'd,</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">To mangle me with that word 'banished'?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="53">Thou fond mad man, hear me but speak a word.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="54">O, thou wilt speak again of banishment.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="55">I'll give thee armour to keep off that word:</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">Adversity's sweet milk, philosophy,</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">To comfort thee, though thou art banished.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="58">Yet 'banished'? Hang up philosophy!</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">Unless philosophy can make a Juliet,</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">Displant a town, reverse a prince's doom,</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">It helps not, it prevails not: talk no more.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="62">O, then I see that madmen have no ears.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="63">How should they, when that wise men have no eyes?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="64">Let me dispute with thee of thy estate.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="65">Thou canst not speak of that thou dost not feel:</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">Wert thou as young as I, Juliet thy love,</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">An hour but married, Tybalt murdered,</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">Doting like me and like me banished,</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">Then mightst thou speak, then mightst thou tear thy hair,</a><br/>
<a NAME="70">And fall upon the ground, as I do now,</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">Taking the measure of an unmade grave.</a><br/>
<p><i>Knocking within</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="72">Arise; one knocks; good Romeo, hide thyself.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="73">Not I; unless the breath of heartsick groans,</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">Mist-like, infold me from the search of eyes.</a><br/>
<p><i>Knocking</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="75">Hark, how they knock! Who's there? Romeo, arise;</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">Thou wilt be taken. Stay awhile! Stand up;</a><br/>
<p><i>Knocking</i></p>
<a NAME="77">Run to my study. By and by! God's will,</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">What simpleness is this! I come, I come!</a><br/>
<p><i>Knocking</i></p>
<a NAME="79">Who knocks so hard? whence come you? what's your will?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="80">[Within]  Let me come in, and you shall know</a><br/>
<a NAME="81">my errand;</a><br/>
<a NAME="82">I come from Lady Juliet.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="83">Welcome, then.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter Nurse</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech24"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="84">O holy friar, O, tell me, holy friar,</a><br/>
<a NAME="85">Where is my lady's lord, where's Romeo?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech25"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="86">There on the ground, with his own tears made drunk.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech26"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="87">O, he is even in my mistress' case,</a><br/>
<a NAME="88">Just in her case! O woful sympathy!</a><br/>
<a NAME="89">Piteous predicament! Even so lies she,</a><br/>
<a NAME="90">Blubbering and weeping, weeping and blubbering.</a><br/>
<a NAME="91">Stand up, stand up; stand, and you be a man:</a><br/>
<a NAME="92">For Juliet's sake, for her sake, rise and stand;</a><br/>
<a NAME="93">Why should you fall into so deep an O?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech27"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="94">Nurse!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech28"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="95">Ah sir! ah sir! Well, death's the end of all.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech29"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="96">Spakest thou of Juliet? how is it with her?</a><br/>
<a NAME="97">Doth she not think me an old murderer,</a><br/>
<a NAME="98">Now I have stain'd the childhood of our joy</a><br/>
<a NAME="99">With blood removed but little from her own?</a><br/>
<a NAME="100">Where is she? and how doth she? and what says</a><br/>
<a NAME="101">My conceal'd lady to our cancell'd love?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech30"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="102">O, she says nothing, sir, but weeps and weeps;</a><br/>
<a NAME="103">And now falls on her bed; and then starts up,</a><br/>
<a NAME="104">And Tybalt calls; and then on Romeo cries,</a><br/>
<a NAME="105">And then down falls again.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech31"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="106">As if that name,</a><br/>
<a NAME="107">Shot from the deadly level of a gun,</a><br/>
<a NAME="108">Did murder her; as that name's cursed hand</a><br/>
<a NAME="109">Murder'd her kinsman. O, tell me, friar, tell me,</a><br/>
<a NAME="110">In what vile part of this anatomy</a><br/>
<a NAME="111">Doth my name lodge? tell me, that I may sack</a><br/>
<a NAME="112">The hateful mansion.</a><br/>
<p><i>Drawing his sword</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech32"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="113">Hold thy desperate hand:</a><br/>
<a NAME="114">Art thou a man? thy form cries out thou art:</a><br/>
<a NAME="115">Thy tears are womanish; thy wild acts denote</a><br/>
<a NAME="116">The unreasonable fury of a beast:</a><br/>
<a NAME="117">Unseemly woman in a seeming man!</a><br/>
<a NAME="118">Or ill-beseeming beast in seeming both!</a><br/>
<a NAME="119">Thou hast amazed me: by my holy order,</a><br/>
<a NAME="120">I thought thy disposition better temper'd.</a><br/>
<a NAME="121">Hast thou slain Tybalt? wilt thou slay thyself?</a><br/>
<a NAME="122">And stay thy lady too that lives in thee,</a><br/>
<a NAME="123">By doing damned hate upon thyself?</a><br/>
<a NAME="124">Why rail'st thou on thy birth, the heaven, and earth?</a><br/>
<a NAME="125">Since birth, and heaven, and earth, all three do meet</a><br/>
<a NAME="126">In thee at once; which thou at once wouldst lose.</a><br/>
<a NAME="127">Fie, fie, thou shamest thy shape, thy love, thy wit;</a><br/>
<a NAME="128">Which, like a usurer, abound'st in all,</a><br/>
<a NAME="129">And usest none in that true use indeed</a><br/>
<a NAME="130">Which should bedeck thy shape, thy love, thy wit:</a><br/>
<a NAME="131">Thy noble shape is but a form of wax,</a><br/>
<a NAME="132">Digressing from the valour of a man;</a><br/>
<a NAME="133">Thy dear love sworn but hollow perjury,</a><br/>
<a NAME="134">Killing that love which thou hast vow'd to cherish;</a><br/>
<a NAME="135">Thy wit, that ornament to shape and love,</a><br/>
<a NAME="136">Misshapen in the conduct of them both,</a><br/>
<a NAME="137">Like powder in a skitless soldier's flask,</a><br/>
<a NAME="138">Is set afire by thine own ignorance,</a><br/>
<a NAME="139">And thou dismember'd with thine own defence.</a><br/>
<a NAME="140">What, rouse thee, man! thy Juliet is alive,</a><br/>
<a NAME="141">For whose dear sake thou wast but lately dead;</a><br/>
<a NAME="142">There art thou happy: Tybalt would kill thee,</a><br/>
<a NAME="143">But thou slew'st Tybalt; there are thou happy too:</a><br/>
<a NAME="144">The law that threaten'd death becomes thy friend</a><br/>
<a NAME="145">And turns it to exile; there art thou happy:</a><br/>
<a NAME="146">A pack of blessings lights up upon thy back;</a><br/>
<a NAME="147">Happiness courts thee in her best array;</a><br/>
<a NAME="148">But, like a misbehaved and sullen wench,</a><br/>
<a NAME="149">Thou pout'st upon thy fortune and thy love:</a><br/>
<a NAME="150">Take heed, take heed, for such die miserable.</a><br/>
<a NAME="151">Go, get thee to thy love, as was decreed,</a><br/>
<a NAME="152">Ascend her chamber, hence and comfort her:</a><br/>
<a NAME="153">But look thou stay not till the watch be set,</a><br/>
<a NAME="154">For then thou canst not pass to Mantua;</a><br/>
<a NAME="155">Where thou shalt live, till we can find a time</a><br/>
<a NAME="156">To blaze your marriage, reconcile your friends,</a><br/>
<a NAME="157">Beg pardon of the prince, and call thee back</a><br/>
<a NAME="158">With twenty hundred thousand times more joy</a><br/>
<a NAME="159">Than thou went'st forth in lamentation.</a><br/>
<a NAME="160">Go before, nurse: commend me to thy lady;</a><br/>
<a NAME="161">And bid her hasten all the house to bed,</a><br/>
<a NAME="162">Which heavy sorrow makes them apt unto:</a><br/>
<a NAME="163">Romeo is coming.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech33"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="164">O Lord, I could have stay'd here all the night</a><br/>
<a NAME="165">To hear good counsel: O, what learning is!</a><br/>
<a NAME="166">My lord, I'll tell my lady you will come.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech34"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="167">Do so, and bid my sweet prepare to chide.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech35"><b>Nurse</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="168">Here, sir, a ring she bid me give you, sir:</a><br/>
<a NAME="169">Hie you, make haste, for it grows very late.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech36"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="170">How well my comfort is revived by this!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech37"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="171">Go hence; good night; and here stands all your state:</a><br/>
<a NAME="172">Either be gone before the watch be set,</a><br/>
<a NAME="173">Or by the break of day disguised from hence:</a><br/>
<a NAME="174">Sojourn in Mantua; I'll find out your man,</a><br/>
<a NAME="175">And he shall signify from time to time</a><br/>
<a NAME="176">Every good hap to you that chances here:</a><br/>
<a NAME="177">Give me thy hand; 'tis late: farewell; good night.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech38"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="178">But that a joy past joy calls out on me,</a><br/>
<a NAME="179">It were a grief, so brief to part with thee: Farewell.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
