<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. Friar Laurence's cell.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter FRIAR LAURENCE and PARIS</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">On Thursday, sir? the time is very short.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>PARIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="2">My father Capulet will have it so;</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">And I am nothing slow to slack his haste.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="4">You say you do not know the lady's mind:</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Uneven is the course, I like it not.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>PARIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="6">Immoderately she weeps for Tybalt's death,</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">And therefore have I little talk'd of love;</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">For Venus smiles not in a house of tears.</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Now, sir, her father counts it dangerous</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">That she doth give her sorrow so much sway,</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">And in his wisdom hastes our marriage,</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">To stop the inundation of her tears;</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">Which, too much minded by herself alone,</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">May be put from her by society:</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">Now do you know the reason of this haste.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="16">[Aside]  I would I knew not why it should be slow'd.</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">Look, sir, here comes the lady towards my cell.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter JULIET</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>PARIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="18">Happily met, my lady and my wife!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="19">That may be, sir, when I may be a wife.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>PARIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="20">That may be must be, love, on Thursday next.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="21">What must be shall be.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="22">That's a certain text.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>PARIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="23">Come you to make confession to this father?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="24">To answer that, I should confess to you.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>PARIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="25">Do not deny to him that you love me.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="26">I will confess to you that I love him.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>PARIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="27">So will ye, I am sure, that you love me.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="28">If I do so, it will be of more price,</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Being spoke behind your back, than to your face.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>PARIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="30">Poor soul, thy face is much abused with tears.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="31">The tears have got small victory by that;</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">For it was bad enough before their spite.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>PARIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="33">Thou wrong'st it, more than tears, with that report.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="34">That is no slander, sir, which is a truth;</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">And what I spake, I spake it to my face.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>PARIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="36">Thy face is mine, and thou hast slander'd it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="37">It may be so, for it is not mine own.</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">Are you at leisure, holy father, now;</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">Or shall I come to you at evening mass?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="40">My leisure serves me, pensive daughter, now.</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">My lord, we must entreat the time alone.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech24"><b>PARIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="42">God shield I should disturb devotion!</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">Juliet, on Thursday early will I rouse ye:</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">Till then, adieu; and keep this holy kiss.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech25"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="45">O shut the door! and when thou hast done so,</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">Come weep with me; past hope, past cure, past help!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech26"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="47">Ah, Juliet, I already know thy grief;</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">It strains me past the compass of my wits:</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">I hear thou must, and nothing may prorogue it,</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">On Thursday next be married to this county.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech27"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="51">Tell me not, friar, that thou hear'st of this,</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">Unless thou tell me how I may prevent it:</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">If, in thy wisdom, thou canst give no help,</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">Do thou but call my resolution wise,</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">And with this knife I'll help it presently.</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">God join'd my heart and Romeo's, thou our hands;</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">And ere this hand, by thee to Romeo seal'd,</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">Shall be the label to another deed,</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">Or my true heart with treacherous revolt</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">Turn to another, this shall slay them both:</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">Therefore, out of thy long-experienced time,</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">Give me some present counsel, or, behold,</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">'Twixt my extremes and me this bloody knife</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">Shall play the umpire, arbitrating that</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">Which the commission of thy years and art</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">Could to no issue of true honour bring.</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">Be not so long to speak; I long to die,</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">If what thou speak'st speak not of remedy.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech28"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="69">Hold, daughter: I do spy a kind of hope,</a><br/>
<a NAME="70">Which craves as desperate an execution.</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">As that is desperate which we would prevent.</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">If, rather than to marry County Paris,</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">Thou hast the strength of will to slay thyself,</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">Then is it likely thou wilt undertake</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">A thing like death to chide away this shame,</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">That copest with death himself to scape from it:</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">And, if thou darest, I'll give thee remedy.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech29"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="78">O, bid me leap, rather than marry Paris,</a><br/>
<a NAME="79">From off the battlements of yonder tower;</a><br/>
<a NAME="80">Or walk in thievish ways; or bid me lurk</a><br/>
<a NAME="81">Where serpents are; chain me with roaring bears;</a><br/>
<a NAME="82">Or shut me nightly in a charnel-house,</a><br/>
<a NAME="83">O'er-cover'd quite with dead men's rattling bones,</a><br/>
<a NAME="84">With reeky shanks and yellow chapless skulls;</a><br/>
<a NAME="85">Or bid me go into a new-made grave</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">And hide me with a dead man in his shroud;</a><br/>
<a NAME="87">Things that, to hear them told, have made me tremble;</a><br/>
<a NAME="88">And I will do it without fear or doubt,</a><br/>
<a NAME="89">To live an unstain'd wife to my sweet love.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech30"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="90">Hold, then; go home, be merry, give consent</a><br/>
<a NAME="91">To marry Paris: Wednesday is to-morrow:</a><br/>
<a NAME="92">To-morrow night look that thou lie alone;</a><br/>
<a NAME="93">Let not thy nurse lie with thee in thy chamber:</a><br/>
<a NAME="94">Take thou this vial, being then in bed,</a><br/>
<a NAME="95">And this distilled liquor drink thou off;</a><br/>
<a NAME="96">When presently through all thy veins shall run</a><br/>
<a NAME="97">A cold and drowsy humour, for no pulse</a><br/>
<a NAME="98">Shall keep his native progress, but surcease:</a><br/>
<a NAME="99">No warmth, no breath, shall testify thou livest;</a><br/>
<a NAME="100">The roses in thy lips and cheeks shall fade</a><br/>
<a NAME="101">To paly ashes, thy eyes' windows fall,</a><br/>
<a NAME="102">Like death, when he shuts up the day of life;</a><br/>
<a NAME="103">Each part, deprived of supple government,</a><br/>
<a NAME="104">Shall, stiff and stark and cold, appear like death:</a><br/>
<a NAME="105">And in this borrow'd likeness of shrunk death</a><br/>
<a NAME="106">Thou shalt continue two and forty hours,</a><br/>
<a NAME="107">And then awake as from a pleasant sleep.</a><br/>
<a NAME="108">Now, when the bridegroom in the morning comes</a><br/>
<a NAME="109">To rouse thee from thy bed, there art thou dead:</a><br/>
<a NAME="110">Then, as the manner of our country is,</a><br/>
<a NAME="111">In thy best robes uncover'd on the bier</a><br/>
<a NAME="112">Thou shalt be borne to that same ancient vault</a><br/>
<a NAME="113">Where all the kindred of the Capulets lie.</a><br/>
<a NAME="114">In the mean time, against thou shalt awake,</a><br/>
<a NAME="115">Shall Romeo by my letters know our drift,</a><br/>
<a NAME="116">And hither shall he come: and he and I</a><br/>
<a NAME="117">Will watch thy waking, and that very night</a><br/>
<a NAME="118">Shall Romeo bear thee hence to Mantua.</a><br/>
<a NAME="119">And this shall free thee from this present shame;</a><br/>
<a NAME="120">If no inconstant toy, nor womanish fear,</a><br/>
<a NAME="121">Abate thy valour in the acting it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech31"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="122">Give me, give me! O, tell not me of fear!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech32"><b>FRIAR LAURENCE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="123">Hold; get you gone, be strong and prosperous</a><br/>
<a NAME="124">In this resolve: I'll send a friar with speed</a><br/>
<a NAME="125">To Mantua, with my letters to thy lord.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech33"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="126">Love give me strength! and strength shall help afford.</a><br/>
<a NAME="127">Farewell, dear father!</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
