<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. Mantua. A street.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter ROMEO</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">If I may trust the flattering truth of sleep,</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">My dreams presage some joyful news at hand:</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">My bosom's lord sits lightly in his throne;</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">And all this day an unaccustom'd spirit</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Lifts me above the ground with cheerful thoughts.</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">I dreamt my lady came and found me dead--</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Strange dream, that gives a dead man leave</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">to think!--</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">And breathed such life with kisses in my lips,</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">That I revived, and was an emperor.</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Ah me! how sweet is love itself possess'd,</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">When but love's shadows are so rich in joy!</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter BALTHASAR, booted</i></p>
<a NAME="13">News from Verona!--How now, Balthasar!</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">Dost thou not bring me letters from the friar?</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">How doth my lady? Is my father well?</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">How fares my Juliet? that I ask again;</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">For nothing can be ill, if she be well.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>BALTHASAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="18">Then she is well, and nothing can be ill:</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">Her body sleeps in Capel's monument,</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">And her immortal part with angels lives.</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">I saw her laid low in her kindred's vault,</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">And presently took post to tell it you:</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">O, pardon me for bringing these ill news,</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">Since you did leave it for my office, sir.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="25">Is it even so? then I defy you, stars!</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">Thou know'st my lodging: get me ink and paper,</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">And hire post-horses; I will hence to-night.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>BALTHASAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="28">I do beseech you, sir, have patience:</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Your looks are pale and wild, and do import</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Some misadventure.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="31">                  Tush, thou art deceived:</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">Leave me, and do the thing I bid thee do.</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">Hast thou no letters to me from the friar?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>BALTHASAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="34">No, my good lord.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="35">                  No matter: get thee gone,</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">And hire those horses; I'll be with thee straight.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit BALTHASAR</i></p>
<a NAME="37">Well, Juliet, I will lie with thee to-night.</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">Let's see for means: O mischief, thou art swift</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">To enter in the thoughts of desperate men!</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">I do remember an apothecary,--</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">And hereabouts he dwells,--which late I noted</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">In tatter'd weeds, with overwhelming brows,</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">Culling of simples; meagre were his looks,</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">Sharp misery had worn him to the bones:</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">And in his needy shop a tortoise hung,</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">An alligator stuff'd, and other skins</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">Of ill-shaped fishes; and about his shelves</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">A beggarly account of empty boxes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">Green earthen pots, bladders and musty seeds,</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">Remnants of packthread and old cakes of roses,</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">Were thinly scatter'd, to make up a show.</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">Noting this penury, to myself I said</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">'An if a man did need a poison now,</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">Whose sale is present death in Mantua,</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">Here lives a caitiff wretch would sell it him.'</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">O, this same thought did but forerun my need;</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">And this same needy man must sell it me.</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">As I remember, this should be the house.</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">Being holiday, the beggar's shop is shut.</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">What, ho! apothecary!</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter Apothecary</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>Apothecary</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="61">Who calls so loud?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="62">Come hither, man. I see that thou art poor:</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">Hold, there is forty ducats: let me have</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">A dram of poison, such soon-speeding gear</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">As will disperse itself through all the veins</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">That the life-weary taker may fall dead</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">And that the trunk may be discharged of breath</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">As violently as hasty powder fired</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">Doth hurry from the fatal cannon's womb.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>Apothecary</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="70">Such mortal drugs I have; but Mantua's law</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">Is death to any he that utters them.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="72">Art thou so bare and full of wretchedness,</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">And fear'st to die? famine is in thy cheeks,</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">Need and oppression starveth in thine eyes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">Contempt and beggary hangs upon thy back;</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">The world is not thy friend nor the world's law;</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">The world affords no law to make thee rich;</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">Then be not poor, but break it, and take this.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>Apothecary</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="79">My poverty, but not my will, consents.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="80">I pay thy poverty, and not thy will.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>Apothecary</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="81">Put this in any liquid thing you will,</a><br/>
<a NAME="82">And drink it off; and, if you had the strength</a><br/>
<a NAME="83">Of twenty men, it would dispatch you straight.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>ROMEO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="84">There is thy gold, worse poison to men's souls,</a><br/>
<a NAME="85">Doing more murders in this loathsome world,</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">Than these poor compounds that thou mayst not sell.</a><br/>
<a NAME="87">I sell thee poison; thou hast sold me none.</a><br/>
<a NAME="88">Farewell: buy food, and get thyself in flesh.</a><br/>
<a NAME="89">Come, cordial and not poison, go with me</a><br/>
<a NAME="90">To Juliet's grave; for there must I use thee.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
