<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE III. Juliet's chamber.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter JULIET and Nurse</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Ay, those attires are best: but, gentle nurse,</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">I pray thee, leave me to my self to-night,</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">For I have need of many orisons</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">To move the heavens to smile upon my state,</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Which, well thou know'st, is cross, and full of sin.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter LADY CAPULET</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>LADY CAPULET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="6">What, are you busy, ho? need you my help?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="7">No, madam; we have cull'd such necessaries</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">As are behoveful for our state to-morrow:</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">So please you, let me now be left alone,</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">And let the nurse this night sit up with you;</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">For, I am sure, you have your hands full all,</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">In this so sudden business.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>LADY CAPULET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="13">Good night:</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">Get thee to bed, and rest; for thou hast need.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt LADY CAPULET and Nurse</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>JULIET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="15">Farewell! God knows when we shall meet again.</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">I have a faint cold fear thrills through my veins,</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">That almost freezes up the heat of life:</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">I'll call them back again to comfort me:</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">Nurse! What should she do here?</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">My dismal scene I needs must act alone.</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">Come, vial.</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">What if this mixture do not work at all?</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Shall I be married then to-morrow morning?</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">No, no: this shall forbid it: lie thou there.</a><br/>
<p><i>Laying down her dagger</i></p>
<a NAME="25">What if it be a poison, which the friar</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">Subtly hath minister'd to have me dead,</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">Lest in this marriage he should be dishonour'd,</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">Because he married me before to Romeo?</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">I fear it is: and yet, methinks, it should not,</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">For he hath still been tried a holy man.</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">How if, when I am laid into the tomb,</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">I wake before the time that Romeo</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">Come to redeem me? there's a fearful point!</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">Shall I not, then, be stifled in the vault,</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">To whose foul mouth no healthsome air breathes in,</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">And there die strangled ere my Romeo comes?</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">Or, if I live, is it not very like,</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">The horrible conceit of death and night,</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">Together with the terror of the place,--</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">As in a vault, an ancient receptacle,</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">Where, for these many hundred years, the bones</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">Of all my buried ancestors are packed:</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">Where bloody Tybalt, yet but green in earth,</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">Lies festering in his shroud; where, as they say,</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">At some hours in the night spirits resort;--</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">Alack, alack, is it not like that I,</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">So early waking, what with loathsome smells,</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">And shrieks like mandrakes' torn out of the earth,</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">That living mortals, hearing them, run mad:--</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">O, if I wake, shall I not be distraught,</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">Environed with all these hideous fears?</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">And madly play with my forefather's joints?</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">And pluck the mangled Tybalt from his shroud?</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">And, in this rage, with some great kinsman's bone,</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">As with a club, dash out my desperate brains?</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">O, look! methinks I see my cousin's ghost</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">Seeking out Romeo, that did spit his body</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">Upon a rapier's point: stay, Tybalt, stay!</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">Romeo, I come! this do I drink to thee.</a><br/>
<p><i>She falls upon her bed, within the curtains</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
