<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. Orchard of Oliver's house.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter ORLANDO and ADAM</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">As I remember, Adam, it was upon this fashion</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">bequeathed me by will but poor a thousand crowns,</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">and, as thou sayest, charged my brother, on his</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">blessing, to breed me well: and there begins my</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">sadness. My brother Jaques he keeps at school, and</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">report speaks goldenly of his profit: for my part,</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">he keeps me rustically at home, or, to speak more</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">properly, stays me here at home unkept; for call you</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">that keeping for a gentleman of my birth, that</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">differs not from the stalling of an ox? His horses</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">are bred better; for, besides that they are fair</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">with their feeding, they are taught their manage,</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">and to that end riders dearly hired: but I, his</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">brother, gain nothing under him but growth; for the</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">which his animals on his dunghills are as much</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">bound to him as I. Besides this nothing that he so</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">plentifully gives me, the something that nature gave</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">me his countenance seems to take from me: he lets</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">me feed with his hinds, bars me the place of a</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">brother, and, as much as in him lies, mines my</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">gentility with my education. This is it, Adam, that</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">grieves me; and the spirit of my father, which I</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">think is within me, begins to mutiny against this</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">servitude: I will no longer endure it, though yet I</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">know no wise remedy how to avoid it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>ADAM</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="26">Yonder comes my master, your brother.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="27">Go apart, Adam, and thou shalt hear how he will</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">shake me up.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter OLIVER</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="29">Now, sir! what make you here?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="30">Nothing: I am not taught to make any thing.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="31">What mar you then, sir?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="32">Marry, sir, I am helping you to mar that which God</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">made, a poor unworthy brother of yours, with idleness.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="34">Marry, sir, be better employed, and be naught awhile.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="35">Shall I keep your hogs and eat husks with them?</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">What prodigal portion have I spent, that I should</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">come to such penury?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="38">Know you where your are, sir?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="39">O, sir, very well; here in your orchard.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="40">Know you before whom, sir?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="41">Ay, better than him I am before knows me. I know</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">you are my eldest brother; and, in the gentle</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">condition of blood, you should so know me. The</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">courtesy of nations allows you my better, in that</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">you are the first-born; but the same tradition</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">takes not away my blood, were there twenty brothers</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">betwixt us: I have as much of my father in me as</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">you; albeit, I confess, your coming before me is</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">nearer to his reverence.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="50">What, boy!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="51">Come, come, elder brother, you are too young in this.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="52">Wilt thou lay hands on me, villain?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="53">I am no villain; I am the youngest son of Sir</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">Rowland de Boys; he was my father, and he is thrice</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">a villain that says such a father begot villains.</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">Wert thou not my brother, I would not take this hand</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">from thy throat till this other had pulled out thy</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">tongue for saying so: thou hast railed on thyself.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>ADAM</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="59">Sweet masters, be patient: for your father's</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">remembrance, be at accord.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="61">Let me go, I say.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="62">I will not, till I please: you shall hear me. My</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">father charged you in his will to give me good</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">education: you have trained me like a peasant,</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">obscuring and hiding from me all gentleman-like</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">qualities. The spirit of my father grows strong in</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">me, and I will no longer endure it: therefore allow</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">me such exercises as may become a gentleman, or</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">give me the poor allottery my father left me by</a><br/>
<a NAME="70">testament; with that I will go buy my fortunes.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="71">And what wilt thou do? beg, when that is spent?</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">Well, sir, get you in: I will not long be troubled</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">with you; you shall have some part of your will: I</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">pray you, leave me.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="75">I will no further offend you than becomes me for my good.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="76">Get you with him, you old dog.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech24"><b>ADAM</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="77">Is 'old dog' my reward? Most true, I have lost my</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">teeth in your service. God be with my old master!</a><br/>
<a NAME="79">he would not have spoke such a word.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt ORLANDO and ADAM</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech25"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="80">Is it even so? begin you to grow upon me? I will</a><br/>
<a NAME="81">physic your rankness, and yet give no thousand</a><br/>
<a NAME="82">crowns neither. Holla, Dennis!</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter DENNIS</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech26"><b>DENNIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="83">Calls your worship?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech27"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="84">Was not Charles, the duke's wrestler, here to speak with me?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech28"><b>DENNIS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="85">So please you, he is here at the door and importunes</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">access to you.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech29"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="87">Call him in.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit DENNIS</i></p>
<a NAME="88">'Twill be a good way; and to-morrow the wrestling is.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter CHARLES</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech30"><b>CHARLES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="89">Good morrow to your worship.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech31"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="90">Good Monsieur Charles, what's the new news at the</a><br/>
<a NAME="91">new court?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech32"><b>CHARLES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="92">There's no news at the court, sir, but the old news:</a><br/>
<a NAME="93">that is, the old duke is banished by his younger</a><br/>
<a NAME="94">brother the new duke; and three or four loving lords</a><br/>
<a NAME="95">have put themselves into voluntary exile with him,</a><br/>
<a NAME="96">whose lands and revenues enrich the new duke;</a><br/>
<a NAME="97">therefore he gives them good leave to wander.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech33"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="98">Can you tell if Rosalind, the duke's daughter, be</a><br/>
<a NAME="99">banished with her father?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech34"><b>CHARLES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="100">O, no; for the duke's daughter, her cousin, so loves</a><br/>
<a NAME="101">her, being ever from their cradles bred together,</a><br/>
<a NAME="102">that she would have followed her exile, or have died</a><br/>
<a NAME="103">to stay behind her. She is at the court, and no</a><br/>
<a NAME="104">less beloved of her uncle than his own daughter; and</a><br/>
<a NAME="105">never two ladies loved as they do.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech35"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="106">Where will the old duke live?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech36"><b>CHARLES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="107">They say he is already in the forest of Arden, and</a><br/>
<a NAME="108">a many merry men with him; and there they live like</a><br/>
<a NAME="109">the old Robin Hood of England: they say many young</a><br/>
<a NAME="110">gentlemen flock to him every day, and fleet the time</a><br/>
<a NAME="111">carelessly, as they did in the golden world.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech37"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="112">What, you wrestle to-morrow before the new duke?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech38"><b>CHARLES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="113">Marry, do I, sir; and I came to acquaint you with a</a><br/>
<a NAME="114">matter. I am given, sir, secretly to understand</a><br/>
<a NAME="115">that your younger brother Orlando hath a disposition</a><br/>
<a NAME="116">to come in disguised against me to try a fall.</a><br/>
<a NAME="117">To-morrow, sir, I wrestle for my credit; and he that</a><br/>
<a NAME="118">escapes me without some broken limb shall acquit him</a><br/>
<a NAME="119">well. Your brother is but young and tender; and,</a><br/>
<a NAME="120">for your love, I would be loath to foil him, as I</a><br/>
<a NAME="121">must, for my own honour, if he come in: therefore,</a><br/>
<a NAME="122">out of my love to you, I came hither to acquaint you</a><br/>
<a NAME="123">withal, that either you might stay him from his</a><br/>
<a NAME="124">intendment or brook such disgrace well as he shall</a><br/>
<a NAME="125">run into, in that it is a thing of his own search</a><br/>
<a NAME="126">and altogether against my will.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech39"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="127">Charles, I thank thee for thy love to me, which</a><br/>
<a NAME="128">thou shalt find I will most kindly requite. I had</a><br/>
<a NAME="129">myself notice of my brother's purpose herein and</a><br/>
<a NAME="130">have by underhand means laboured to dissuade him from</a><br/>
<a NAME="131">it, but he is resolute. I'll tell thee, Charles:</a><br/>
<a NAME="132">it is the stubbornest young fellow of France, full</a><br/>
<a NAME="133">of ambition, an envious emulator of every man's</a><br/>
<a NAME="134">good parts, a secret and villanous contriver against</a><br/>
<a NAME="135">me his natural brother: therefore use thy</a><br/>
<a NAME="136">discretion; I had as lief thou didst break his neck</a><br/>
<a NAME="137">as his finger. And thou wert best look to't; for if</a><br/>
<a NAME="138">thou dost him any slight disgrace or if he do not</a><br/>
<a NAME="139">mightily grace himself on thee, he will practise</a><br/>
<a NAME="140">against thee by poison, entrap thee by some</a><br/>
<a NAME="141">treacherous device and never leave thee till he</a><br/>
<a NAME="142">hath ta'en thy life by some indirect means or other;</a><br/>
<a NAME="143">for, I assure thee, and almost with tears I speak</a><br/>
<a NAME="144">it, there is not one so young and so villanous this</a><br/>
<a NAME="145">day living. I speak but brotherly of him; but</a><br/>
<a NAME="146">should I anatomize him to thee as he is, I must</a><br/>
<a NAME="147">blush and weep and thou must look pale and wonder.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech40"><b>CHARLES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="148">I am heartily glad I came hither to you. If he come</a><br/>
<a NAME="149">to-morrow, I'll give him his payment: if ever he go</a><br/>
<a NAME="150">alone again, I'll never wrestle for prize more: and</a><br/>
<a NAME="151">so God keep your worship!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech41"><b>OLIVER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="152">Farewell, good Charles.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit CHARLES</i></p>
<a NAME="153">Now will I stir this gamester: I hope I shall see</a><br/>
<a NAME="154">an end of him; for my soul, yet I know not why,</a><br/>
<a NAME="155">hates nothing more than he. Yet he's gentle, never</a><br/>
<a NAME="156">schooled and yet learned, full of noble device, of</a><br/>
<a NAME="157">all sorts enchantingly beloved, and indeed so much</a><br/>
<a NAME="158">in the heart of the world, and especially of my own</a><br/>
<a NAME="159">people, who best know him, that I am altogether</a><br/>
<a NAME="160">misprised: but it shall not be so long; this</a><br/>
<a NAME="161">wrestler shall clear all: nothing remains but that</a><br/>
<a NAME="162">I kindle the boy thither; which now I'll go about.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
