<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. The Forest of Arden.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter DUKE SENIOR, AMIENS, and two or three Lords, like foresters</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Now, my co-mates and brothers in exile,</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">Hath not old custom made this life more sweet</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">Than that of painted pomp? Are not these woods</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">More free from peril than the envious court?</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Here feel we but the penalty of Adam,</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">The seasons' difference, as the icy fang</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">And churlish chiding of the winter's wind,</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">Which, when it bites and blows upon my body,</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Even till I shrink with cold, I smile and say</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">'This is no flattery: these are counsellors</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">That feelingly persuade me what I am.'</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">Sweet are the uses of adversity,</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">Which, like the toad, ugly and venomous,</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">Wears yet a precious jewel in his head;</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">And this our life exempt from public haunt</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">Finds tongues in trees, books in the running brooks,</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">Sermons in stones and good in every thing.</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">I would not change it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>AMIENS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="19">Happy is your grace,</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">That can translate the stubbornness of fortune</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">Into so quiet and so sweet a style.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="22">Come, shall we go and kill us venison?</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">And yet it irks me the poor dappled fools,</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">Being native burghers of this desert city,</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">Should in their own confines with forked heads</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">Have their round haunches gored.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>First Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="27">Indeed, my lord,</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">The melancholy Jaques grieves at that,</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">And, in that kind, swears you do more usurp</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Than doth your brother that hath banish'd you.</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">To-day my Lord of Amiens and myself</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">Did steal behind him as he lay along</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">Under an oak whose antique root peeps out</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">Upon the brook that brawls along this wood:</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">To the which place a poor sequester'd stag,</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">That from the hunter's aim had ta'en a hurt,</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">Did come to languish, and indeed, my lord,</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">The wretched animal heaved forth such groans</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">That their discharge did stretch his leathern coat</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">Almost to bursting, and the big round tears</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">Coursed one another down his innocent nose</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">In piteous chase; and thus the hairy fool</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">Much marked of the melancholy Jaques,</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">Stood on the extremest verge of the swift brook,</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">Augmenting it with tears.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="46">But what said Jaques?</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">Did he not moralize this spectacle?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>First Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="48">O, yes, into a thousand similes.</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">First, for his weeping into the needless stream;</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">'Poor deer,' quoth he, 'thou makest a testament</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">As worldlings do, giving thy sum of more</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">To that which had too much:' then, being there alone,</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">Left and abandon'd of his velvet friends,</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">''Tis right:' quoth he; 'thus misery doth part</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">The flux of company:' anon a careless herd,</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">Full of the pasture, jumps along by him</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">And never stays to greet him; 'Ay' quoth Jaques,</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">'Sweep on, you fat and greasy citizens;</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">'Tis just the fashion: wherefore do you look</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">Upon that poor and broken bankrupt there?'</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">Thus most invectively he pierceth through</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">The body of the country, city, court,</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">Yea, and of this our life, swearing that we</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">Are mere usurpers, tyrants and what's worse,</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">To fright the animals and to kill them up</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">In their assign'd and native dwelling-place.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="67">And did you leave him in this contemplation?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>Second Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="68">We did, my lord, weeping and commenting</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">Upon the sobbing deer.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="70">Show me the place:</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">I love to cope him in these sullen fits,</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">For then he's full of matter.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>First Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="73">I'll bring you to him straight.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
