<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE III. Before OLIVER'S house.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter ORLANDO and ADAM, meeting</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Who's there?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>ADAM</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="2">What, my young master? O, my gentle master!</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">O my sweet master! O you memory</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">Of old Sir Rowland! why, what make you here?</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Why are you virtuous? why do people love you?</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">And wherefore are you gentle, strong and valiant?</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Why would you be so fond to overcome</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">The bonny priser of the humorous duke?</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Your praise is come too swiftly home before you.</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">Know you not, master, to some kind of men</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Their graces serve them but as enemies?</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">No more do yours: your virtues, gentle master,</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">Are sanctified and holy traitors to you.</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">O, what a world is this, when what is comely</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">Envenoms him that bears it!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="16">Why, what's the matter?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>ADAM</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="17">O unhappy youth!</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">Come not within these doors; within this roof</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">The enemy of all your graces lives:</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">Your brother--no, no brother; yet the son--</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">Yet not the son, I will not call him son</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">Of him I was about to call his father--</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Hath heard your praises, and this night he means</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">To burn the lodging where you use to lie</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">And you within it: if he fail of that,</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">He will have other means to cut you off.</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">I overheard him and his practises.</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">This is no place; this house is but a butchery:</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Abhor it, fear it, do not enter it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="30">Why, whither, Adam, wouldst thou have me go?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>ADAM</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="31">No matter whither, so you come not here.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="32">What, wouldst thou have me go and beg my food?</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">Or with a base and boisterous sword enforce</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">A thievish living on the common road?</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">This I must do, or know not what to do:</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">Yet this I will not do, do how I can;</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">I rather will subject me to the malice</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">Of a diverted blood and bloody brother.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>ADAM</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="39">But do not so. I have five hundred crowns,</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">The thrifty hire I saved under your father,</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">Which I did store to be my foster-nurse</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">When service should in my old limbs lie lame</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">And unregarded age in corners thrown:</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">Take that, and He that doth the ravens feed,</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">Yea, providently caters for the sparrow,</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">Be comfort to my age! Here is the gold;</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">And all this I give you. Let me be your servant:</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">Though I look old, yet I am strong and lusty;</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">For in my youth I never did apply</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">Hot and rebellious liquors in my blood,</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">Nor did not with unbashful forehead woo</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">The means of weakness and debility;</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">Therefore my age is as a lusty winter,</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">Frosty, but kindly: let me go with you;</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">I'll do the service of a younger man</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">In all your business and necessities.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="57">O good old man, how well in thee appears</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">The constant service of the antique world,</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">When service sweat for duty, not for meed!</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">Thou art not for the fashion of these times,</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">Where none will sweat but for promotion,</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">And having that, do choke their service up</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">Even with the having: it is not so with thee.</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">But, poor old man, thou prunest a rotten tree,</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">That cannot so much as a blossom yield</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">In lieu of all thy pains and husbandry</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">But come thy ways; well go along together,</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">And ere we have thy youthful wages spent,</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">We'll light upon some settled low content.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>ADAM</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="70">Master, go on, and I will follow thee,</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">To the last gasp, with truth and loyalty.</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">From seventeen years till now almost fourscore</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">Here lived I, but now live here no more.</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">At seventeen years many their fortunes seek;</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">But at fourscore it is too late a week:</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">Yet fortune cannot recompense me better</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">Than to die well and not my master's debtor.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
