<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE IV. The forest.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter DUKE SENIOR, AMIENS, JAQUES, ORLANDO, OLIVER, and CELIA</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Dost thou believe, Orlando, that the boy</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">Can do all this that he hath promised?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="3">I sometimes do believe, and sometimes do not;</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">As those that fear they hope, and know they fear.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter ROSALIND, SILVIUS, and PHEBE</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>ROSALIND</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="5">Patience once more, whiles our compact is urged:</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">You say, if I bring in your Rosalind,</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">You will bestow her on Orlando here?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="8">That would I, had I kingdoms to give with her.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>ROSALIND</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="9">And you say, you will have her, when I bring her?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="10">That would I, were I of all kingdoms king.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>ROSALIND</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="11">You say, you'll marry me, if I be willing?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>PHEBE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="12">That will I, should I die the hour after.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>ROSALIND</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="13">But if you do refuse to marry me,</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">You'll give yourself to this most faithful shepherd?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>PHEBE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="15">So is the bargain.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>ROSALIND</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="16">You say, that you'll have Phebe, if she will?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>SILVIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="17">Though to have her and death were both one thing.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>ROSALIND</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="18">I have promised to make all this matter even.</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">Keep you your word, O duke, to give your daughter;</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">You yours, Orlando, to receive his daughter:</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">Keep your word, Phebe, that you'll marry me,</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">Or else refusing me, to wed this shepherd:</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Keep your word, Silvius, that you'll marry her.</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">If she refuse me: and from hence I go,</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">To make these doubts all even.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt ROSALIND and CELIA</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="26">I do remember in this shepherd boy</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">Some lively touches of my daughter's favour.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="28">My lord, the first time that I ever saw him</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Methought he was a brother to your daughter:</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">But, my good lord, this boy is forest-born,</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">And hath been tutor'd in the rudiments</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">Of many desperate studies by his uncle,</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">Whom he reports to be a great magician,</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">Obscured in the circle of this forest.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter TOUCHSTONE and AUDREY</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>JAQUES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="35">There is, sure, another flood toward, and these</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">couples are coming to the ark. Here comes a pair of</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">very strange beasts, which in all tongues are called fools.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>TOUCHSTONE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="38">Salutation and greeting to you all!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>JAQUES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="39">Good my lord, bid him welcome: this is the</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">motley-minded gentleman that I have so often met in</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">the forest: he hath been a courtier, he swears.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>TOUCHSTONE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="42">If any man doubt that, let him put me to my</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">purgation. I have trod a measure; I have flattered</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">a lady; I have been politic with my friend, smooth</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">with mine enemy; I have undone three tailors; I have</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">had four quarrels, and like to have fought one.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>JAQUES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="47">And how was that ta'en up?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>TOUCHSTONE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="48">Faith, we met, and found the quarrel was upon the</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">seventh cause.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>JAQUES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="50">How seventh cause? Good my lord, like this fellow.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="51">I like him very well.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech24"><b>TOUCHSTONE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="52">God 'ild you, sir; I desire you of the like. I</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">press in here, sir, amongst the rest of the country</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">copulatives, to swear and to forswear: according as</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">marriage binds and blood breaks: a poor virgin,</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">sir, an ill-favoured thing, sir, but mine own; a poor</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">humour of mine, sir, to take that that no man else</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">will: rich honesty dwells like a miser, sir, in a</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">poor house; as your pearl in your foul oyster.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech25"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="60">By my faith, he is very swift and sententious.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech26"><b>TOUCHSTONE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="61">According to the fool's bolt, sir, and such dulcet diseases.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech27"><b>JAQUES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="62">But, for the seventh cause; how did you find the</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">quarrel on the seventh cause?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech28"><b>TOUCHSTONE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="64">Upon a lie seven times removed:--bear your body more</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">seeming, Audrey:--as thus, sir. I did dislike the</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">cut of a certain courtier's beard: he sent me word,</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">if I said his beard was not cut well, he was in the</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">mind it was: this is called the Retort Courteous.</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">If I sent him word again 'it was not well cut,' he</a><br/>
<a NAME="70">would send me word, he cut it to please himself:</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">this is called the Quip Modest. If again 'it was</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">not well cut,' he disabled my judgment: this is</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">called the Reply Churlish. If again 'it was not</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">well cut,' he would answer, I spake not true: this</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">is called the Reproof Valiant. If again 'it was not</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">well cut,' he would say I lied: this is called the</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">Counter-cheque Quarrelsome: and so to the Lie</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">Circumstantial and the Lie Direct.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech29"><b>JAQUES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="79">And how oft did you say his beard was not well cut?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech30"><b>TOUCHSTONE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="80">I durst go no further than the Lie Circumstantial,</a><br/>
<a NAME="81">nor he durst not give me the Lie Direct; and so we</a><br/>
<a NAME="82">measured swords and parted.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech31"><b>JAQUES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="83">Can you nominate in order now the degrees of the lie?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech32"><b>TOUCHSTONE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="84">O sir, we quarrel in print, by the book; as you have</a><br/>
<a NAME="85">books for good manners: I will name you the degrees.</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">The first, the Retort Courteous; the second, the</a><br/>
<a NAME="87">Quip Modest; the third, the Reply Churlish; the</a><br/>
<a NAME="88">fourth, the Reproof Valiant; the fifth, the</a><br/>
<a NAME="89">Countercheque Quarrelsome; the sixth, the Lie with</a><br/>
<a NAME="90">Circumstance; the seventh, the Lie Direct. All</a><br/>
<a NAME="91">these you may avoid but the Lie Direct; and you may</a><br/>
<a NAME="92">avoid that too, with an If. I knew when seven</a><br/>
<a NAME="93">justices could not take up a quarrel, but when the</a><br/>
<a NAME="94">parties were met themselves, one of them thought but</a><br/>
<a NAME="95">of an If, as, 'If you said so, then I said so;' and</a><br/>
<a NAME="96">they shook hands and swore brothers. Your If is the</a><br/>
<a NAME="97">only peacemaker; much virtue in If.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech33"><b>JAQUES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="98">Is not this a rare fellow, my lord? he's as good at</a><br/>
<a NAME="99">any thing and yet a fool.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech34"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="100">He uses his folly like a stalking-horse and under</a><br/>
<a NAME="101">the presentation of that he shoots his wit.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter HYMEN, ROSALIND, and CELIA</i></p>
<p><i>Still Music</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech35"><b>HYMEN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="102">        Then is there mirth in heaven,</a><br/>
<a NAME="103">When earthly things made even</a><br/>
<a NAME="104">Atone together.</a><br/>
<a NAME="105">Good duke, receive thy daughter</a><br/>
<a NAME="106">Hymen from heaven brought her,</a><br/>
<a NAME="107">Yea, brought her hither,</a><br/>
<a NAME="108">That thou mightst join her hand with his</a><br/>
<a NAME="109">Whose heart within his bosom is.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech36"><b>ROSALIND</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="110">[To DUKE SENIOR]  To you I give myself, for I am yours.</a><br/>
<p><i>To ORLANDO</i></p>
<a NAME="111">To you I give myself, for I am yours.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech37"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="112">If there be truth in sight, you are my daughter.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech38"><b>ORLANDO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="113">If there be truth in sight, you are my Rosalind.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech39"><b>PHEBE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="114">If sight and shape be true,</a><br/>
<a NAME="115">Why then, my love adieu!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech40"><b>ROSALIND</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="116">I'll have no father, if you be not he:</a><br/>
<a NAME="117">I'll have no husband, if you be not he:</a><br/>
<a NAME="118">Nor ne'er wed woman, if you be not she.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech41"><b>HYMEN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="119">        Peace, ho! I bar confusion:</a><br/>
<a NAME="120">'Tis I must make conclusion</a><br/>
<a NAME="121">Of these most strange events:</a><br/>
<a NAME="122">Here's eight that must take hands</a><br/>
<a NAME="123">To join in Hymen's bands,</a><br/>
<a NAME="124">If truth holds true contents.</a><br/>
<a NAME="125">You and you no cross shall part:</a><br/>
<a NAME="126">You and you are heart in heart</a><br/>
<a NAME="127">You to his love must accord,</a><br/>
<a NAME="128">Or have a woman to your lord:</a><br/>
<a NAME="129">You and you are sure together,</a><br/>
<a NAME="130">As the winter to foul weather.</a><br/>
<a NAME="131">Whiles a wedlock-hymn we sing,</a><br/>
<a NAME="132">Feed yourselves with questioning;</a><br/>
<a NAME="133">That reason wonder may diminish,</a><br/>
<a NAME="134">How thus we met, and these things finish.</a><br/>
<a NAME="135">SONG.</a><br/>
<a NAME="136">Wedding is great Juno's crown:</a><br/>
<a NAME="137">O blessed bond of board and bed!</a><br/>
<a NAME="138">'Tis Hymen peoples every town;</a><br/>
<a NAME="139">High wedlock then be honoured:</a><br/>
<a NAME="140">Honour, high honour and renown,</a><br/>
<a NAME="141">To Hymen, god of every town!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech42"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="142">O my dear niece, welcome thou art to me!</a><br/>
<a NAME="143">Even daughter, welcome, in no less degree.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech43"><b>PHEBE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="144">I will not eat my word, now thou art mine;</a><br/>
<a NAME="145">Thy faith my fancy to thee doth combine.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter JAQUES DE BOYS</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech44"><b>JAQUES DE BOYS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="146">Let me have audience for a word or two:</a><br/>
<a NAME="147">I am the second son of old Sir Rowland,</a><br/>
<a NAME="148">That bring these tidings to this fair assembly.</a><br/>
<a NAME="149">Duke Frederick, hearing how that every day</a><br/>
<a NAME="150">Men of great worth resorted to this forest,</a><br/>
<a NAME="151">Address'd a mighty power; which were on foot,</a><br/>
<a NAME="152">In his own conduct, purposely to take</a><br/>
<a NAME="153">His brother here and put him to the sword:</a><br/>
<a NAME="154">And to the skirts of this wild wood he came;</a><br/>
<a NAME="155">Where meeting with an old religious man,</a><br/>
<a NAME="156">After some question with him, was converted</a><br/>
<a NAME="157">Both from his enterprise and from the world,</a><br/>
<a NAME="158">His crown bequeathing to his banish'd brother,</a><br/>
<a NAME="159">And all their lands restored to them again</a><br/>
<a NAME="160">That were with him exiled. This to be true,</a><br/>
<a NAME="161">I do engage my life.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech45"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="162">Welcome, young man;</a><br/>
<a NAME="163">Thou offer'st fairly to thy brothers' wedding:</a><br/>
<a NAME="164">To one his lands withheld, and to the other</a><br/>
<a NAME="165">A land itself at large, a potent dukedom.</a><br/>
<a NAME="166">First, in this forest, let us do those ends</a><br/>
<a NAME="167">That here were well begun and well begot:</a><br/>
<a NAME="168">And after, every of this happy number</a><br/>
<a NAME="169">That have endured shrewd days and nights with us</a><br/>
<a NAME="170">Shall share the good of our returned fortune,</a><br/>
<a NAME="171">According to the measure of their states.</a><br/>
<a NAME="172">Meantime, forget this new-fall'n dignity</a><br/>
<a NAME="173">And fall into our rustic revelry.</a><br/>
<a NAME="174">Play, music! And you, brides and bridegrooms all,</a><br/>
<a NAME="175">With measure heap'd in joy, to the measures fall.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech46"><b>JAQUES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="176">Sir, by your patience. If I heard you rightly,</a><br/>
<a NAME="177">The duke hath put on a religious life</a><br/>
<a NAME="178">And thrown into neglect the pompous court?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech47"><b>JAQUES DE BOYS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="179">He hath.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech48"><b>JAQUES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="180">To him will I : out of these convertites</a><br/>
<a NAME="181">There is much matter to be heard and learn'd.</a><br/>
<p><i>To DUKE SENIOR</i></p>
<a NAME="182">You to your former honour I bequeath;</a><br/>
<a NAME="183">Your patience and your virtue well deserves it:</a><br/>
<p><i>To ORLANDO</i></p>
<a NAME="184">You to a love that your true faith doth merit:</a><br/>
<p><i>To OLIVER</i></p>
<a NAME="185">You to your land and love and great allies:</a><br/>
<p><i>To SILVIUS</i></p>
<a NAME="186">You to a long and well-deserved bed:</a><br/>
<p><i>To TOUCHSTONE</i></p>
<a NAME="187">And you to wrangling; for thy loving voyage</a><br/>
<a NAME="188">Is but for two months victuall'd. So, to your pleasures:</a><br/>
<a NAME="189">I am for other than for dancing measures.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech49"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="190">Stay, Jaques, stay.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech50"><b>JAQUES</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="191">To see no pastime I	what you would have</a><br/>
<a NAME="192">I'll stay to know at your abandon'd cave.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech51"><b>DUKE SENIOR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="193">Proceed, proceed: we will begin these rites,</a><br/>
<a NAME="194">As we do trust they'll end, in true delights.</a><br/>
<p><i>A dance</i></p>
<a NAME="195">EPILOGUE</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech52"><b>ROSALIND</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="196">It is not the fashion to see the lady the epilogue;</a><br/>
<a NAME="197">but it is no more unhandsome than to see the lord</a><br/>
<a NAME="198">the prologue. If it be true that good wine needs</a><br/>
<a NAME="199">no bush, 'tis true that a good play needs no</a><br/>
<a NAME="200">epilogue; yet to good wine they do use good bushes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="201">and good plays prove the better by the help of good</a><br/>
<a NAME="202">epilogues. What a case am I in then, that am</a><br/>
<a NAME="203">neither a good epilogue nor cannot insinuate with</a><br/>
<a NAME="204">you in the behalf of a good play! I am not</a><br/>
<a NAME="205">furnished like a beggar, therefore to beg will not</a><br/>
<a NAME="206">become me: my way is to conjure you; and I'll begin</a><br/>
<a NAME="207">with the women. I charge you, O women, for the love</a><br/>
<a NAME="208">you bear to men, to like as much of this play as</a><br/>
<a NAME="209">please you: and I charge you, O men, for the love</a><br/>
<a NAME="210">you bear to women--as I perceive by your simpering,</a><br/>
<a NAME="211">none of you hates them--that between you and the</a><br/>
<a NAME="212">women the play may please. If I were a woman I</a><br/>
<a NAME="213">would kiss as many of you as had beards that pleased</a><br/>
<a NAME="214">me, complexions that liked me and breaths that I</a><br/>
<a NAME="215">defied not: and, I am sure, as many as have good</a><br/>
<a NAME="216">beards or good faces or sweet breaths will, for my</a><br/>
<a NAME="217">kind offer, when I make curtsy, bid me farewell.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
