<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE II. A room in LEONATO's house.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter LEONATO and ANTONIO, meeting</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>LEONATO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">How now, brother! Where is my cousin, your son?</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">hath he provided this music?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="3">He is very busy about it. But, brother, I can tell</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">you strange news that you yet dreamt not of.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>LEONATO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="5">Are they good?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="6">As the event stamps them: but they have a good</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">cover; they show well outward. The prince and Count</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">Claudio, walking in a thick-pleached alley in mine</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">orchard, were thus much overheard by a man of mine:</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">the prince discovered to Claudio that he loved my</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">niece your daughter and meant to acknowledge it</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">this night in a dance: and if he found her</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">accordant, he meant to take the present time by the</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">top and instantly break with you of it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>LEONATO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="15">Hath the fellow any wit that told you this?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="16">A good sharp fellow: I will send for him; and</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">question him yourself.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>LEONATO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="18">No, no; we will hold it as a dream till it appear</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">itself: but I will acquaint my daughter withal,</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">that she may be the better prepared for an answer,</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">if peradventure this be true. Go you and tell her of it.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter Attendants</i></p>
<a NAME="22">Cousins, you know what you have to do. O, I cry you</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">mercy, friend; go you with me, and I will use your</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">skill. Good cousin, have a care this busy time.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>

