<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE III. The same.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter DON JOHN and CONRADE</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>CONRADE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">What the good-year, my lord! why are you thus out</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">of measure sad?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>DON JOHN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="3">There is no measure in the occasion that breeds;</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">therefore the sadness is without limit.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>CONRADE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="5">You should hear reason.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>DON JOHN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="6">And when I have heard it, what blessing brings it?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>CONRADE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="7">If not a present remedy, at least a patient</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">sufferance.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>DON JOHN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="9">I wonder that thou, being, as thou sayest thou art,</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">born under Saturn, goest about to apply a moral</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">medicine to a mortifying mischief. I cannot hide</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">what I am: I must be sad when I have cause and smile</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">at no man's jests, eat when I have stomach and wait</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">for no man's leisure, sleep when I am drowsy and</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">tend on no man's business, laugh when I am merry and</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">claw no man in his humour.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>CONRADE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="17">Yea, but you must not make the full show of this</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">till you may do it without controlment. You have of</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">late stood out against your brother, and he hath</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">ta'en you newly into his grace; where it is</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">impossible you should take true root but by the</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">fair weather that you make yourself: it is needful</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">that you frame the season for your own harvest.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>DON JOHN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="24">I had rather be a canker in a hedge than a rose in</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">his grace, and it better fits my blood to be</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">disdained of all than to fashion a carriage to rob</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">love from any: in this, though I cannot be said to</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">be a flattering honest man, it must not be denied</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">but I am a plain-dealing villain. I am trusted with</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">a muzzle and enfranchised with a clog; therefore I</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">have decreed not to sing in my cage. If I had my</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">mouth, I would bite; if I had my liberty, I would do</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">my liking: in the meantime let me be that I am and</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">seek not to alter me.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>CONRADE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="35">Can you make no use of your discontent?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>DON JOHN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="36">I make all use of it, for I use it only.</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">Who comes here?</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter BORACHIO</i></p>
<a NAME="38">What news, Borachio?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>BORACHIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="39">I came yonder from a great supper: the prince your</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">brother is royally entertained by Leonato: and I</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">can give you intelligence of an intended marriage.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>DON JOHN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="42">Will it serve for any model to build mischief on?</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">What is he for a fool that betroths himself to</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">unquietness?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>BORACHIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="45">Marry, it is your brother's right hand.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>DON JOHN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="46">Who? the most exquisite Claudio?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>BORACHIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="47">Even he.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>DON JOHN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="48">A proper squire! And who, and who? which way looks</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">he?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>BORACHIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="50">Marry, on Hero, the daughter and heir of Leonato.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>DON JOHN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="51">A very forward March-chick! How came you to this?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>BORACHIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="52">Being entertained for a perfumer, as I was smoking a</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">musty room, comes me the prince and Claudio, hand</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">in hand in sad conference: I whipt me behind the</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">arras; and there heard it agreed upon that the</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">prince should woo Hero for himself, and having</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">obtained her, give her to Count Claudio.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>DON JOHN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="58">Come, come, let us thither: this may prove food to</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">my displeasure. That young start-up hath all the</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">glory of my overthrow: if I can cross him any way, I</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">bless myself every way. You are both sure, and will assist me?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>CONRADE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="62">To the death, my lord.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>DON JOHN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="63">Let us to the great supper: their cheer is the</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">greater that I am subdued. Would the cook were of</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">my mind! Shall we go prove what's to be done?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>BORACHIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="66">We'll wait upon your lordship.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>

