<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE II. LEONATO'S garden.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter BENEDICK and MARGARET, meeting</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Pray thee, sweet Mistress Margaret, deserve well at</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">my hands by helping me to the speech of Beatrice.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>MARGARET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="3">Will you then write me a sonnet in praise of my beauty?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="4">In so high a style, Margaret, that no man living</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">shall come over it; for, in most comely truth, thou</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">deservest it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>MARGARET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="7">To have no man come over me! why, shall I always</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">keep below stairs?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="9">Thy wit is as quick as the greyhound's mouth; it catches.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>MARGARET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="10">And yours as blunt as the fencer's foils, which hit,</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">but hurt not.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="12">A most manly wit, Margaret; it will not hurt a</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">woman: and so, I pray thee, call Beatrice: I give</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">thee the bucklers.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>MARGARET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="15">Give us the swords; we have bucklers of our own.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="16">If you use them, Margaret, you must put in the</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">pikes with a vice; and they are dangerous weapons for maids.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>MARGARET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="18">Well, I will call Beatrice to you, who I think hath legs.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="19">And therefore will come.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit MARGARET</i></p>
<p><i>Sings</i></p>
<a NAME="20">The god of love,</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">That sits above,</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">And knows me, and knows me,</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">How pitiful I deserve,--</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">I mean in singing; but in loving, Leander the good</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">swimmer, Troilus the first employer of panders, and</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">a whole bookful of these quondam carpet-mangers,</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">whose names yet run smoothly in the even road of a</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">blank verse, why, they were never so truly turned</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">over and over as my poor self in love. Marry, I</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">cannot show it in rhyme; I have tried: I can find</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">out no rhyme to 'lady' but 'baby,' an innocent</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">rhyme; for 'scorn,' 'horn,' a hard rhyme; for,</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">'school,' 'fool,' a babbling rhyme; very ominous</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">endings: no, I was not born under a rhyming planet,</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">nor I cannot woo in festival terms.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter BEATRICE</i></p>
<a NAME="36">Sweet Beatrice, wouldst thou come when I called thee?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>BEATRICE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="37">Yea, signior, and depart when you bid me.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="38">O, stay but till then!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>BEATRICE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="39">'Then' is spoken; fare you well now: and yet, ere</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">I go, let me go with that I came; which is, with</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">knowing what hath passed between you and Claudio.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="42">Only foul words; and thereupon I will kiss thee.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>BEATRICE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="43">Foul words is but foul wind, and foul wind is but</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">foul breath, and foul breath is noisome; therefore I</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">will depart unkissed.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="46">Thou hast frighted the word out of his right sense,</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">so forcible is thy wit. But I must tell thee</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">plainly, Claudio undergoes my challenge; and either</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">I must shortly hear from him, or I will subscribe</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">him a coward. And, I pray thee now, tell me for</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">which of my bad parts didst thou first fall in love with me?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>BEATRICE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="52">For them all together; which maintained so politic</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">a state of evil that they will not admit any good</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">part to intermingle with them. But for which of my</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">good parts did you first suffer love for me?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="56">Suffer love! a good epithet! I do suffer love</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">indeed, for I love thee against my will.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>BEATRICE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="58">In spite of your heart, I think; alas, poor heart!</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">If you spite it for my sake, I will spite it for</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">yours; for I will never love that which my friend hates.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="61">Thou and I are too wise to woo peaceably.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>BEATRICE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="62">It appears not in this confession: there's not one</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">wise man among twenty that will praise himself.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="64">An old, an old instance, Beatrice, that lived in</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">the lime of good neighbours. If a man do not erect</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">in this age his own tomb ere he dies, he shall live</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">no longer in monument than the bell rings and the</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">widow weeps.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech24"><b>BEATRICE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="69">And how long is that, think you?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech25"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="70">Question: why, an hour in clamour and a quarter in</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">rheum: therefore is it most expedient for the</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">wise, if Don Worm, his conscience, find no</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">impediment to the contrary, to be the trumpet of his</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">own virtues, as I am to myself. So much for</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">praising myself, who, I myself will bear witness, is</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">praiseworthy: and now tell me, how doth your cousin?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech26"><b>BEATRICE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="77">Very ill.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech27"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="78">And how do you?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech28"><b>BEATRICE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="79">Very ill too.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech29"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="80">Serve God, love me and mend. There will I leave</a><br/>
<a NAME="81">you too, for here comes one in haste.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter URSULA</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech30"><b>URSULA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="82">Madam, you must come to your uncle. Yonder's old</a><br/>
<a NAME="83">coil at home: it is proved my Lady Hero hath been</a><br/>
<a NAME="84">falsely accused, the prince and Claudio mightily</a><br/>
<a NAME="85">abused; and Don John is the author of all, who is</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">fed and gone. Will you come presently?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech31"><b>BEATRICE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="87">Will you go hear this news, signior?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech32"><b>BENEDICK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="88">I will live in thy heart, die in thy lap, and be</a><br/>
<a NAME="89">buried in thy eyes; and moreover I will go with</a><br/>
<a NAME="90">thee to thy uncle's.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
