<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. LEONATO'S garden.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter HERO, MARGARET, and URSULA</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Good Margaret, run thee to the parlor;</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">There shalt thou find my cousin Beatrice</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">Proposing with the prince and Claudio:</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">Whisper her ear and tell her, I and Ursula</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Walk in the orchard and our whole discourse</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">Is all of her; say that thou overheard'st us;</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">And bid her steal into the pleached bower,</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">Where honeysuckles, ripen'd by the sun,</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Forbid the sun to enter, like favourites,</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">Made proud by princes, that advance their pride</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Against that power that bred it: there will she hide her,</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">To listen our purpose.  This is thy office;</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">Bear thee well in it and leave us alone.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>MARGARET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="14">I'll make her come, I warrant you, presently.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="15">Now, Ursula, when Beatrice doth come,</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">As we do trace this alley up and down,</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">Our talk must only be of Benedick.</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">When I do name him, let it be thy part</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">To praise him more than ever man did merit:</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">My talk to thee must be how Benedick</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">Is sick in love with Beatrice. Of this matter</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">Is little Cupid's crafty arrow made,</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">That only wounds by hearsay.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter BEATRICE, behind</i></p>
<a NAME="24">Now begin;</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">For look where Beatrice, like a lapwing, runs</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">Close by the ground, to hear our conference.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>URSULA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="27">The pleasant'st angling is to see the fish</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">Cut with her golden oars the silver stream,</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">And greedily devour the treacherous bait:</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">So angle we for Beatrice; who even now</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">Is couched in the woodbine coverture.</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">Fear you not my part of the dialogue.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="33">Then go we near her, that her ear lose nothing</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">Of the false sweet bait that we lay for it.</a><br/>
<p><i>Approaching the bower</i></p>
<a NAME="35">No, truly, Ursula, she is too disdainful;</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">I know her spirits are as coy and wild</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">As haggerds of the rock.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>URSULA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="38">But are you sure</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">That Benedick loves Beatrice so entirely?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="40">So says the prince and my new-trothed lord.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>URSULA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="41">And did they bid you tell her of it, madam?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="42">They did entreat me to acquaint her of it;</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">But I persuaded them, if they loved Benedick,</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">To wish him wrestle with affection,</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">And never to let Beatrice know of it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>URSULA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="46">Why did you so? Doth not the gentleman</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">Deserve as full as fortunate a bed</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">As ever Beatrice shall couch upon?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="49">O god of love! I know he doth deserve</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">As much as may be yielded to a man:</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">But Nature never framed a woman's heart</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">Of prouder stuff than that of Beatrice;</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">Disdain and scorn ride sparkling in her eyes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">Misprising what they look on, and her wit</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">Values itself so highly that to her</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">All matter else seems weak: she cannot love,</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">Nor take no shape nor project of affection,</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">She is so self-endeared.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>URSULA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="59">Sure, I think so;</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">And therefore certainly it were not good</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">She knew his love, lest she make sport at it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="62">Why, you speak truth. I never yet saw man,</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">How wise, how noble, young, how rarely featured,</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">But she would spell him backward: if fair-faced,</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">She would swear the gentleman should be her sister;</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">If black, why, Nature, drawing of an antique,</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">Made a foul blot; if tall, a lance ill-headed;</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">If low, an agate very vilely cut;</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">If speaking, why, a vane blown with all winds;</a><br/>
<a NAME="70">If silent, why, a block moved with none.</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">So turns she every man the wrong side out</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">And never gives to truth and virtue that</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">Which simpleness and merit purchaseth.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>URSULA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="74">Sure, sure, such carping is not commendable.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="75">No, not to be so odd and from all fashions</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">As Beatrice is, cannot be commendable:</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">But who dare tell her so? If I should speak,</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">She would mock me into air; O, she would laugh me</a><br/>
<a NAME="79">Out of myself, press me to death with wit.</a><br/>
<a NAME="80">Therefore let Benedick, like cover'd fire,</a><br/>
<a NAME="81">Consume away in sighs, waste inwardly:</a><br/>
<a NAME="82">It were a better death than die with mocks,</a><br/>
<a NAME="83">Which is as bad as die with tickling.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>URSULA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="84">Yet tell her of it: hear what she will say.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="85">No; rather I will go to Benedick</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">And counsel him to fight against his passion.</a><br/>
<a NAME="87">And, truly, I'll devise some honest slanders</a><br/>
<a NAME="88">To stain my cousin with: one doth not know</a><br/>
<a NAME="89">How much an ill word may empoison liking.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>URSULA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="90">O, do not do your cousin such a wrong.</a><br/>
<a NAME="91">She cannot be so much without true judgment--</a><br/>
<a NAME="92">Having so swift and excellent a wit</a><br/>
<a NAME="93">As she is prized to have--as to refuse</a><br/>
<a NAME="94">So rare a gentleman as Signior Benedick.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="95">He is the only man of Italy.</a><br/>
<a NAME="96">Always excepted my dear Claudio.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>URSULA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="97">I pray you, be not angry with me, madam,</a><br/>
<a NAME="98">Speaking my fancy: Signior Benedick,</a><br/>
<a NAME="99">For shape, for bearing, argument and valour,</a><br/>
<a NAME="100">Goes foremost in report through Italy.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="101">Indeed, he hath an excellent good name.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>URSULA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="102">His excellence did earn it, ere he had it.</a><br/>
<a NAME="103">When are you married, madam?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="104">Why, every day, to-morrow. Come, go in:</a><br/>
<a NAME="105">I'll show thee some attires, and have thy counsel</a><br/>
<a NAME="106">Which is the best to furnish me to-morrow.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech24"><b>URSULA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="107">She's limed, I warrant you: we have caught her, madam.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech25"><b>HERO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="108">If it proves so, then loving goes by haps:</a><br/>
<a NAME="109">Some Cupid kills with arrows, some with traps.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt HERO and URSULA</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech26"><b>BEATRICE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="110">[Coming forward]</a><br/>
<a NAME="111">What fire is in mine ears? Can this be true?</a><br/>
<a NAME="112">Stand I condemn'd for pride and scorn so much?</a><br/>
<a NAME="113">Contempt, farewell! and maiden pride, adieu!</a><br/>
<a NAME="114">No glory lives behind the back of such.</a><br/>
<a NAME="115">And, Benedick, love on; I will requite thee,</a><br/>
<a NAME="116">Taming my wild heart to thy loving hand:</a><br/>
<a NAME="117">If thou dost love, my kindness shall incite thee</a><br/>
<a NAME="118">To bind our loves up in a holy band;</a><br/>
<a NAME="119">For others say thou dost deserve, and I</a><br/>
<a NAME="120">Believe it better than reportingly.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
