<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE VII. Belmont. A room in PORTIA'S house.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Flourish of cornets. Enter PORTIA, with the PRINCE OF MOROCCO, and their trains</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Go draw aside the curtains and discover</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">The several caskets to this noble prince.</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">Now make your choice.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>MOROCCO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="4">The first, of gold, who this inscription bears,</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">'Who chooseth me shall gain what many men desire;'</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">The second, silver, which this promise carries,</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">'Who chooseth me shall get as much as he deserves;'</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">This third, dull lead, with warning all as blunt,</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">'Who chooseth me must give and hazard all he hath.'</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">How shall I know if I do choose the right?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="11">The one of them contains my picture, prince:</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">If you choose that, then I am yours withal.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>MOROCCO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="13">Some god direct my judgment! Let me see;</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">I will survey the inscriptions back again.</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">What says this leaden casket?</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">'Who chooseth me must give and hazard all he hath.'</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">Must give: for what? for lead? hazard for lead?</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">This casket threatens. Men that hazard all</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">Do it in hope of fair advantages:</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">A golden mind stoops not to shows of dross;</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">I'll then nor give nor hazard aught for lead.</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">What says the silver with her virgin hue?</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">'Who chooseth me shall get as much as he deserves.'</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">As much as he deserves! Pause there, Morocco,</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">And weigh thy value with an even hand:</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">If thou be'st rated by thy estimation,</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">Thou dost deserve enough; and yet enough</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">May not extend so far as to the lady:</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">And yet to be afeard of my deserving</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Were but a weak disabling of myself.</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">As much as I deserve! Why, that's the lady:</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">I do in birth deserve her, and in fortunes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">In graces and in qualities of breeding;</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">But more than these, in love I do deserve.</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">What if I stray'd no further, but chose here?</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">Let's see once more this saying graved in gold</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">'Who chooseth me shall gain what many men desire.'</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">Why, that's the lady; all the world desires her;</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">From the four corners of the earth they come,</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">To kiss this shrine, this mortal-breathing saint:</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">The Hyrcanian deserts and the vasty wilds</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">Of wide Arabia are as thoroughfares now</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">For princes to come view fair Portia:</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">The watery kingdom, whose ambitious head</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">Spits in the face of heaven, is no bar</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">To stop the foreign spirits, but they come,</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">As o'er a brook, to see fair Portia.</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">One of these three contains her heavenly picture.</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">Is't like that lead contains her? 'Twere damnation</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">To think so base a thought: it were too gross</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">To rib her cerecloth in the obscure grave.</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">Or shall I think in silver she's immured,</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">Being ten times undervalued to tried gold?</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">O sinful thought! Never so rich a gem</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">Was set in worse than gold. They have in England</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">A coin that bears the figure of an angel</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">Stamped in gold, but that's insculp'd upon;</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">But here an angel in a golden bed</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">Lies all within. Deliver me the key:</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">Here do I choose, and thrive I as I may!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="61">There, take it, prince; and if my form lie there,</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">Then I am yours.</a><br/>
<p><i>He unlocks the golden casket</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>MOROCCO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="63">                  O hell! what have we here?</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">A carrion Death, within whose empty eye</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">There is a written scroll! I'll read the writing.</a><br/>
<p><i>Reads</i></p>
<a NAME="66">All that glitters is not gold;</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">Often have you heard that told:</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">Many a man his life hath sold</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">But my outside to behold:</a><br/>
<a NAME="70">Gilded tombs do worms enfold.</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">Had you been as wise as bold,</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">Young in limbs, in judgment old,</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">Your answer had not been inscroll'd:</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">Fare you well; your suit is cold.</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">Cold, indeed; and labour lost:</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">Then, farewell, heat, and welcome, frost!</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">Portia, adieu. I have too grieved a heart</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">To take a tedious leave: thus losers part.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit with his train. Flourish of cornets</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="79">A gentle riddance. Draw the curtains, go.</a><br/>
<a NAME="80">Let all of his complexion choose me so.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
