<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE IV. Belmont. A room in PORTIA'S house.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter PORTIA, NERISSA, LORENZO, JESSICA, and BALTHASAR</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>LORENZO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Madam, although I speak it in your presence,</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">You have a noble and a true conceit</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">Of godlike amity; which appears most strongly</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">In bearing thus the absence of your lord.</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">But if you  knew to whom you show this honour,</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">How true a gentleman you send relief,</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">How dear a lover of my lord your husband,</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">I know you would be prouder of the work</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Than customary bounty can enforce you.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="10">I never did repent for doing good,</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Nor shall not now: for in companions</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">That do converse and waste the time together,</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">Whose souls do bear an equal yoke Of love,</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">There must be needs a like proportion</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">Of lineaments, of manners and of spirit;</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">Which makes me think that this Antonio,</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">Being the bosom lover of my lord,</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">Must needs be like my lord. If it be so,</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">How little is the cost I have bestow'd</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">In purchasing the semblance of my soul</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">From out the state of hellish misery!</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">This comes too near the praising of myself;</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Therefore no more of it: hear other things.</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">Lorenzo, I commit into your hands</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">The husbandry and manage of my house</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">Until my lord's return: for mine own part,</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">I have toward heaven breathed a secret vow</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">To live in prayer and contemplation,</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Only attended by Nerissa here,</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Until her husband and my lord's return:</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">There is a monastery two miles off;</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">And there will we abide. I do desire you</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">Not to deny this imposition;</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">The which my love and some necessity</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">Now lays upon you.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>LORENZO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="36">                  Madam, with all my heart;</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">I shall obey you in all fair commands.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="38">My people do already know my mind,</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">And will acknowledge you and Jessica</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">In place of Lord Bassanio and myself.</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">And so farewell, till we shall meet again.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>LORENZO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="42">Fair thoughts and happy hours attend on you!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>JESSICA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="43">I wish your ladyship all heart's content.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="44">I thank you for your wish, and am well pleased</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">To wish it back on you: fare you well Jessica.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt JESSICA and LORENZO</i></p>
<a NAME="46">Now, Balthasar,</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">As I have ever found thee honest-true,</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">So let me find thee still. Take this same letter,</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">And use thou all the endeavour of a man</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">In speed to Padua: see thou render this</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">Into my cousin's hand, Doctor Bellario;</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">And, look, what notes and garments he doth give thee,</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">Bring them, I pray thee, with imagined speed</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">Unto the tranect, to the common ferry</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">Which trades to Venice. Waste no time in words,</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">But get thee gone: I shall be there before thee.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>BALTHASAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="57">Madam, I go with all convenient speed.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="58">Come on, Nerissa; I have work in hand</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">That you yet know not of: we'll see our husbands</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">Before they think of us.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="61">Shall they see us?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="62">They shall, Nerissa; but in such a habit,</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">That they shall think we are accomplished</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">With that we lack. I'll hold thee any wager,</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">When we are both accoutred like young men,</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">I'll prove the prettier fellow of the two,</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">And wear my dagger with the braver grace,</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">And speak between the change of man and boy</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">With a reed voice, and turn two mincing steps</a><br/>
<a NAME="70">Into a manly stride, and speak of frays</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">Like a fine bragging youth, and tell quaint lies,</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">How honourable ladies sought my love,</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">Which I denying, they fell sick and died;</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">I could not do withal; then I'll repent,</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">And wish for all that, that I had not killed them;</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">And twenty of these puny lies I'll tell,</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">That men shall swear I have discontinued school</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">Above a twelvemonth. I have within my mind</a><br/>
<a NAME="79">A thousand raw tricks of these bragging Jacks,</a><br/>
<a NAME="80">Which I will practise.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="81">Why, shall we turn to men?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="82">Fie, what a question's that,</a><br/>
<a NAME="83">If thou wert near a lewd interpreter!</a><br/>
<a NAME="84">But come, I'll tell thee all my whole device</a><br/>
<a NAME="85">When I am in my coach, which stays for us</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">At the park gate; and therefore haste away,</a><br/>
<a NAME="87">For we must measure twenty miles to-day.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
