<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE II. Belmont. A room in PORTIA'S house.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter PORTIA and NERISSA</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech33"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="190">By my troth, Nerissa, my little body is aweary of</a><br/>
<a NAME="191">this great world.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech34"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="192">You would be, sweet madam, if your miseries were in</a><br/>
<a NAME="193">the same abundance as your good fortunes are: and</a><br/>
<a NAME="194">yet, for aught I see, they are as sick that surfeit</a><br/>
<a NAME="195">with too much as they that starve with nothing. It</a><br/>
<a NAME="196">is no mean happiness therefore, to be seated in the</a><br/>
<a NAME="197">mean: superfluity comes sooner by white hairs, but</a><br/>
<a NAME="198">competency lives longer.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech35"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="199">Good sentences and well pronounced.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech36"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="200">They would be better, if well followed.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech37"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="201">If to do were as easy as to know what were good to</a><br/>
<a NAME="202">do, chapels had been churches and poor men's</a><br/>
<a NAME="203">cottages princes' palaces. It is a good divine that</a><br/>
<a NAME="204">follows his own instructions: I can easier teach</a><br/>
<a NAME="205">twenty what were good to be done, than be one of the</a><br/>
<a NAME="206">twenty to follow mine own teaching. The brain may</a><br/>
<a NAME="207">devise laws for the blood, but a hot temper leaps</a><br/>
<a NAME="208">o'er a cold decree: such a hare is madness the</a><br/>
<a NAME="209">youth, to skip o'er the meshes of good counsel the</a><br/>
<a NAME="210">cripple. But this reasoning is not in the fashion to</a><br/>
<a NAME="211">choose me a husband. O me, the word 'choose!' I may</a><br/>
<a NAME="212">neither choose whom I would nor refuse whom I</a><br/>
<a NAME="213">dislike; so is the will of a living daughter curbed</a><br/>
<a NAME="214">by the will of a dead father. Is it not hard,</a><br/>
<a NAME="215">Nerissa, that I cannot choose one nor refuse none?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech38"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="216">Your father was ever virtuous; and holy men at their</a><br/>
<a NAME="217">death have good inspirations: therefore the lottery,</a><br/>
<a NAME="218">that he hath devised in these three chests of gold,</a><br/>
<a NAME="219">silver and lead, whereof who chooses his meaning</a><br/>
<a NAME="220">chooses you, will, no doubt, never be chosen by any</a><br/>
<a NAME="221">rightly but one who shall rightly love. But what</a><br/>
<a NAME="222">warmth is there in your affection towards any of</a><br/>
<a NAME="223">these princely suitors that are already come?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech39"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="224">I pray thee, over-name them; and as thou namest</a><br/>
<a NAME="225">them, I will describe them; and, according to my</a><br/>
<a NAME="226">description, level at my affection.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech40"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="227">First, there is the Neapolitan prince.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech41"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="228">Ay, that's a colt indeed, for he doth nothing but</a><br/>
<a NAME="229">talk of his horse; and he makes it a great</a><br/>
<a NAME="230">appropriation to his own good parts, that he can</a><br/>
<a NAME="231">shoe him himself. I am much afeard my lady his</a><br/>
<a NAME="232">mother played false with a smith.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech42"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="233">Then there is the County Palatine.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech43"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="234">He doth nothing but frown, as who should say 'If you</a><br/>
<a NAME="235">will not have me, choose:' he hears merry tales and</a><br/>
<a NAME="236">smiles not: I fear he will prove the weeping</a><br/>
<a NAME="237">philosopher when he grows old, being so full of</a><br/>
<a NAME="238">unmannerly sadness in his youth. I had rather be</a><br/>
<a NAME="239">married to a death's-head with a bone in his mouth</a><br/>
<a NAME="240">than to either of these. God defend me from these</a><br/>
<a NAME="241">two!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech44"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="242">How say you by the French lord, Monsieur Le Bon?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech45"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="243">God made him, and therefore let him pass for a man.</a><br/>
<a NAME="244">In truth, I know it is a sin to be a mocker: but,</a><br/>
<a NAME="245">he! why, he hath a horse better than the</a><br/>
<a NAME="246">Neapolitan's, a better bad habit of frowning than</a><br/>
<a NAME="247">the Count Palatine; he is every man in no man; if a</a><br/>
<a NAME="248">throstle sing, he falls straight a capering: he will</a><br/>
<a NAME="249">fence with his own shadow: if I should marry him, I</a><br/>
<a NAME="250">should marry twenty husbands. If he would despise me</a><br/>
<a NAME="251">I would forgive him, for if he love me to madness, I</a><br/>
<a NAME="252">shall never requite him.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech46"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="253">What say you, then, to Falconbridge, the young baron</a><br/>
<a NAME="254">of England?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech47"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="255">You know I say nothing to him, for he understands</a><br/>
<a NAME="256">not me, nor I him: he hath neither Latin, French,</a><br/>
<a NAME="257">nor Italian, and you will come into the court and</a><br/>
<a NAME="258">swear that I have a poor pennyworth in the English.</a><br/>
<a NAME="259">He is a proper man's picture, but, alas, who can</a><br/>
<a NAME="260">converse with a dumb-show? How oddly he is suited!</a><br/>
<a NAME="261">I think he bought his doublet in Italy, his round</a><br/>
<a NAME="262">hose in France, his bonnet in Germany and his</a><br/>
<a NAME="263">behavior every where.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech48"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="264">What think you of the Scottish lord, his neighbour?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech49"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="265">That he hath a neighbourly charity in him, for he</a><br/>
<a NAME="266">borrowed a box of the ear of the Englishman and</a><br/>
<a NAME="267">swore he would pay him again when he was able: I</a><br/>
<a NAME="268">think the Frenchman became his surety and sealed</a><br/>
<a NAME="269">under for another.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech50"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="270">How like you the young German, the Duke of Saxony's nephew?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech51"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="271">Very vilely in the morning, when he is sober, and</a><br/>
<a NAME="272">most vilely in the afternoon, when he is drunk: when</a><br/>
<a NAME="273">he is best, he is a little worse than a man, and</a><br/>
<a NAME="274">when he is worst, he is little better than a beast:</a><br/>
<a NAME="275">and the worst fall that ever fell, I hope I shall</a><br/>
<a NAME="276">make shift to go without him.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech52"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="277">If he should offer to choose, and choose the right</a><br/>
<a NAME="278">casket, you should refuse to perform your father's</a><br/>
<a NAME="279">will, if you should refuse to accept him.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech53"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="280">Therefore, for fear of the worst, I pray thee, set a</a><br/>
<a NAME="281">deep glass of rhenish wine on the contrary casket,</a><br/>
<a NAME="282">for if the devil be within and that temptation</a><br/>
<a NAME="283">without, I know he will choose it. I will do any</a><br/>
<a NAME="284">thing, Nerissa, ere I'll be married to a sponge.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech54"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="285">You need not fear, lady, the having any of these</a><br/>
<a NAME="286">lords: they have acquainted me with their</a><br/>
<a NAME="287">determinations; which is, indeed, to return to their</a><br/>
<a NAME="288">home and to trouble you with no more suit, unless</a><br/>
<a NAME="289">you may be won by some other sort than your father's</a><br/>
<a NAME="290">imposition depending on the caskets.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech55"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="291">If I live to be as old as Sibylla, I will die as</a><br/>
<a NAME="292">chaste as Diana, unless I be obtained by the manner</a><br/>
<a NAME="293">of my father's will. I am glad this parcel of wooers</a><br/>
<a NAME="294">are so reasonable, for there is not one among them</a><br/>
<a NAME="295">but I dote on his very absence, and I pray God grant</a><br/>
<a NAME="296">them a fair departure.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech56"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="297">Do you not remember, lady, in your father's time, a</a><br/>
<a NAME="298">Venetian, a scholar and a soldier, that came hither</a><br/>
<a NAME="299">in company of the Marquis of Montferrat?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech57"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="300">Yes, yes, it was Bassanio; as I think, he was so called.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech58"><b>NERISSA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="301">True, madam: he, of all the men that ever my foolish</a><br/>
<a NAME="302">eyes looked upon, was the best deserving a fair lady.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech59"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="303">I remember him well, and I remember him worthy of</a><br/>
<a NAME="304">thy praise.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter a Serving-man</i></p>
<a NAME="305">How now! what news?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech60"><b>Servant</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="306">The four strangers seek for you, madam, to take</a><br/>
<a NAME="307">their leave: and there is a forerunner come from a</a><br/>
<a NAME="308">fifth, the Prince of Morocco, who brings word the</a><br/>
<a NAME="309">prince his master will be here to-night.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech61"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="310">If I could bid the fifth welcome with so good a</a><br/>
<a NAME="311">heart as I can bid the other four farewell, I should</a><br/>
<a NAME="312">be glad of his approach: if he have the condition</a><br/>
<a NAME="313">of a saint and the complexion of a devil, I had</a><br/>
<a NAME="314">rather he should shrive me than wive me. Come,</a><br/>
<a NAME="315">Nerissa. Sirrah, go before.</a><br/>
<a NAME="316">Whiles we shut the gates</a><br/>
<a NAME="317">upon one wooer, another knocks at the door.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
