<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. Belmont. A room in PORTIA'S house.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Flourish of cornets. Enter the PRINCE OF MOROCCO  and his train; PORTIA, NERISSA, and others attending</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>MOROCCO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Mislike me not for my complexion,</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">The shadow'd livery of the burnish'd sun,</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">To whom I am a neighbour and near bred.</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">Bring me the fairest creature northward born,</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Where Phoebus' fire scarce thaws the icicles,</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">And let us make incision for your love,</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">To prove whose blood is reddest, his or mine.</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">I tell thee, lady, this aspect of mine</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Hath fear'd the valiant: by my love I swear</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">The best-regarded virgins of our clime</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Have loved it too: I would not change this hue,</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">Except to steal your thoughts, my gentle queen.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="13">In terms of choice I am not solely led</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">By nice direction of a maiden's eyes;</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">Besides, the lottery of my destiny</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">Bars me the right of voluntary choosing:</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">But if my father had not scanted me</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">And hedged me by his wit, to yield myself</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">His wife who wins me by that means I told you,</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">Yourself, renowned prince, then stood as fair</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">As any comer I have look'd on yet</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">For my affection.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>MOROCCO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="23">                  Even for that I thank you:</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">Therefore, I pray you, lead me to the caskets</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">To try my fortune. By this scimitar</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">That slew the Sophy and a Persian prince</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">That won three fields of Sultan Solyman,</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">I would outstare the sternest eyes that look,</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Outbrave the heart most daring on the earth,</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Pluck the young sucking cubs from the she-bear,</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">Yea, mock the lion when he roars for prey,</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">To win thee, lady. But, alas the while!</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">If Hercules and Lichas play at dice</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">Which is the better man, the greater throw</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">May turn by fortune from the weaker hand:</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">So is Alcides beaten by his page;</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">And so may I, blind fortune leading me,</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">Miss that which one unworthier may attain,</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">And die with grieving.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="40">You must take your chance,</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">And either not attempt to choose at all</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">Or swear before you choose, if you choose wrong</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">Never to speak to lady afterward</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">In way of marriage: therefore be advised.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>MOROCCO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="45">Nor will not. Come, bring me unto my chance.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>PORTIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="46">First, forward to the temple: after dinner</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">Your hazard shall be made.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>MOROCCO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="48">Good fortune then!</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">To make me blest or cursed'st among men.</a><br/>
<p><i>Cornets, and exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
