<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE III. Venice. A public place.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter BASSANIO and SHYLOCK</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Three thousand ducats; well.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>BASSANIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="2">Ay, sir, for three months.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="3">For three months; well.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>BASSANIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="4">For the which, as I told you, Antonio shall be bound.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="5">Antonio shall become bound; well.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>BASSANIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="6">May you stead me? will you pleasure me? shall I</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">know your answer?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="8">Three thousand ducats for three months and Antonio bound.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>BASSANIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="9">Your answer to that.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="10">Antonio is a good man.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>BASSANIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="11">Have you heard any imputation to the contrary?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="12">Oh, no, no, no, no: my meaning in saying he is a</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">good man is to have you understand me that he is</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">sufficient. Yet his means are in supposition: he</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">hath an argosy bound to Tripolis, another to the</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">Indies; I understand moreover, upon the Rialto, he</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">hath a third at Mexico, a fourth for England, and</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">other ventures he hath, squandered abroad. But ships</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">are but boards, sailors but men: there be land-rats</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">and water-rats, water-thieves and land-thieves, I</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">mean pirates, and then there is the peril of waters,</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">winds and rocks. The man is, notwithstanding,</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">sufficient. Three thousand ducats; I think I may</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">take his bond.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>BASSANIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="25">Be assured you may.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="26">I will be assured I may; and, that I may be assured,</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">I will bethink me. May I speak with Antonio?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>BASSANIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="28">If it please you to dine with us.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="29">Yes, to smell pork; to eat of the habitation which</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">your prophet the Nazarite conjured the devil into. I</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">will buy with you, sell with you, talk with you,</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">walk with you, and so following, but I will not eat</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">with you, drink with you, nor pray with you. What</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">news on the Rialto? Who is he comes here?</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter ANTONIO</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>BASSANIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="35">This is Signior Antonio.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="36">[Aside]  How like a fawning publican he looks!</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">I hate him for he is a Christian,</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">But more for that in low simplicity</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">He lends out money gratis and brings down</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">The rate of usance here with us in Venice.</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">If I can catch him once upon the hip,</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">I will feed fat the ancient grudge I bear him.</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">He hates our sacred nation, and he rails,</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">Even there where merchants most do congregate,</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">On me, my bargains and my well-won thrift,</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">Which he calls interest. Cursed be my tribe,</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">If I forgive him!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>BASSANIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="48">                  Shylock, do you hear?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="49">I am debating of my present store,</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">And, by the near guess of my memory,</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">I cannot instantly raise up the gross</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">Of full three thousand ducats. What of that?</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">Tubal, a wealthy Hebrew of my tribe,</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">Will furnish me. But soft! how many months</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">Do you desire?</a><br/>
<p><i>To ANTONIO</i></p>
<a NAME="56">Rest you fair, good signior;</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">Your worship was the last man in our mouths.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="58">Shylock, although I neither lend nor borrow</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">By taking nor by giving of excess,</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">Yet, to supply the ripe wants of my friend,</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">I'll break a custom. Is he yet possess'd</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">How much ye would?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="63">                  Ay, ay, three thousand ducats.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="64">And for three months.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="65">I had forgot; three months; you told me so.</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">Well then, your bond; and let me see; but hear you;</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">Methought you said you neither lend nor borrow</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">Upon advantage.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech24"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="69">                  I do never use it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech25"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="70">When Jacob grazed his uncle Laban's sheep--</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">This Jacob from our holy Abram was,</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">As his wise mother wrought in his behalf,</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">The third possessor; ay, he was the third--</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech26"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="74">And what of him? did he take interest?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech27"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="75">No, not take interest, not, as you would say,</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">Directly interest: mark what Jacob did.</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">When Laban and himself were compromised</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">That all the eanlings which were streak'd and pied</a><br/>
<a NAME="79">Should fall as Jacob's hire, the ewes, being rank,</a><br/>
<a NAME="80">In the end of autumn turned to the rams,</a><br/>
<a NAME="81">And, when the work of generation was</a><br/>
<a NAME="82">Between these woolly breeders in the act,</a><br/>
<a NAME="83">The skilful shepherd peel'd me certain wands,</a><br/>
<a NAME="84">And, in the doing of the deed of kind,</a><br/>
<a NAME="85">He stuck them up before the fulsome ewes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">Who then conceiving did in eaning time</a><br/>
<a NAME="87">Fall parti-colour'd lambs, and those were Jacob's.</a><br/>
<a NAME="88">This was a way to thrive, and he was blest:</a><br/>
<a NAME="89">And thrift is blessing, if men steal it not.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech28"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="90">This was a venture, sir, that Jacob served for;</a><br/>
<a NAME="91">A thing not in his power to bring to pass,</a><br/>
<a NAME="92">But sway'd and fashion'd by the hand of heaven.</a><br/>
<a NAME="93">Was this inserted to make interest good?</a><br/>
<a NAME="94">Or is your gold and silver ewes and rams?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech29"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="95">I cannot tell; I make it breed as fast:</a><br/>
<a NAME="96">But note me, signior.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech30"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="97">Mark you this, Bassanio,</a><br/>
<a NAME="98">The devil can cite Scripture for his purpose.</a><br/>
<a NAME="99">An evil soul producing holy witness</a><br/>
<a NAME="100">Is like a villain with a smiling cheek,</a><br/>
<a NAME="101">A goodly apple rotten at the heart:</a><br/>
<a NAME="102">O, what a goodly outside falsehood hath!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech31"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="103">Three thousand ducats; 'tis a good round sum.</a><br/>
<a NAME="104">Three months from twelve; then, let me see; the rate--</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech32"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="105">Well, Shylock, shall we be beholding to you?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech33"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="106">Signior Antonio, many a time and oft</a><br/>
<a NAME="107">In the Rialto you have rated me</a><br/>
<a NAME="108">About my moneys and my usances:</a><br/>
<a NAME="109">Still have I borne it with a patient shrug,</a><br/>
<a NAME="110">For sufferance is the badge of all our tribe.</a><br/>
<a NAME="111">You call me misbeliever, cut-throat dog,</a><br/>
<a NAME="112">And spit upon my Jewish gaberdine,</a><br/>
<a NAME="113">And all for use of that which is mine own.</a><br/>
<a NAME="114">Well then, it now appears you need my help:</a><br/>
<a NAME="115">Go to, then; you come to me, and you say</a><br/>
<a NAME="116">'Shylock, we would have moneys:' you say so;</a><br/>
<a NAME="117">You, that did void your rheum upon my beard</a><br/>
<a NAME="118">And foot me as you spurn a stranger cur</a><br/>
<a NAME="119">Over your threshold: moneys is your suit</a><br/>
<a NAME="120">What should I say to you? Should I not say</a><br/>
<a NAME="121">'Hath a dog money? is it possible</a><br/>
<a NAME="122">A cur can lend three thousand ducats?' Or</a><br/>
<a NAME="123">Shall I bend low and in a bondman's key,</a><br/>
<a NAME="124">With bated breath and whispering humbleness, Say this;</a><br/>
<a NAME="125">'Fair sir, you spit on me on Wednesday last;</a><br/>
<a NAME="126">You spurn'd me such a day; another time</a><br/>
<a NAME="127">You call'd me dog; and for these courtesies</a><br/>
<a NAME="128">I'll lend you thus much moneys'?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech34"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="129">I am as like to call thee so again,</a><br/>
<a NAME="130">To spit on thee again, to spurn thee too.</a><br/>
<a NAME="131">If thou wilt lend this money, lend it not</a><br/>
<a NAME="132">As to thy friends; for when did friendship take</a><br/>
<a NAME="133">A breed for barren metal of his friend?</a><br/>
<a NAME="134">But lend it rather to thine enemy,</a><br/>
<a NAME="135">Who, if he break, thou mayst with better face</a><br/>
<a NAME="136">Exact the penalty.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech35"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="137">                  Why, look you, how you storm!</a><br/>
<a NAME="138">I would be friends with you and have your love,</a><br/>
<a NAME="139">Forget the shames that you have stain'd me with,</a><br/>
<a NAME="140">Supply your present wants and take no doit</a><br/>
<a NAME="141">Of usance for my moneys, and you'll not hear me:</a><br/>
<a NAME="142">This is kind I offer.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech36"><b>BASSANIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="143">This were kindness.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech37"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="144">This kindness will I show.</a><br/>
<a NAME="145">Go with me to a notary, seal me there</a><br/>
<a NAME="146">Your single bond; and, in a merry sport,</a><br/>
<a NAME="147">If you repay me not on such a day,</a><br/>
<a NAME="148">In such a place, such sum or sums as are</a><br/>
<a NAME="149">Express'd in the condition, let the forfeit</a><br/>
<a NAME="150">Be nominated for an equal pound</a><br/>
<a NAME="151">Of your fair flesh, to be cut off and taken</a><br/>
<a NAME="152">In what part of your body pleaseth me.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech38"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="153">Content, i' faith: I'll seal to such a bond</a><br/>
<a NAME="154">And say there is much kindness in the Jew.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech39"><b>BASSANIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="155">You shall not seal to such a bond for me:</a><br/>
<a NAME="156">I'll rather dwell in my necessity.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech40"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="157">Why, fear not, man; I will not forfeit it:</a><br/>
<a NAME="158">Within these two months, that's a month before</a><br/>
<a NAME="159">This bond expires, I do expect return</a><br/>
<a NAME="160">Of thrice three times the value of this bond.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech41"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="161">O father Abram, what these Christians are,</a><br/>
<a NAME="162">Whose own hard dealings teaches them suspect</a><br/>
<a NAME="163">The thoughts of others! Pray you, tell me this;</a><br/>
<a NAME="164">If he should break his day, what should I gain</a><br/>
<a NAME="165">By the exaction of the forfeiture?</a><br/>
<a NAME="166">A pound of man's flesh taken from a man</a><br/>
<a NAME="167">Is not so estimable, profitable neither,</a><br/>
<a NAME="168">As flesh of muttons, beefs, or goats. I say,</a><br/>
<a NAME="169">To buy his favour, I extend this friendship:</a><br/>
<a NAME="170">If he will take it, so; if not, adieu;</a><br/>
<a NAME="171">And, for my love, I pray you wrong me not.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech42"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="172">Yes Shylock, I will seal unto this bond.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech43"><b>SHYLOCK</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="173">Then meet me forthwith at the notary's;</a><br/>
<a NAME="174">Give him direction for this merry bond,</a><br/>
<a NAME="175">And I will go and purse the ducats straight,</a><br/>
<a NAME="176">See to my house, left in the fearful guard</a><br/>
<a NAME="177">Of an unthrifty knave, and presently</a><br/>
<a NAME="178">I will be with you.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech44"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="179">Hie thee, gentle Jew.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit Shylock</i></p>
<a NAME="180">The Hebrew will turn Christian: he grows kind.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech45"><b>BASSANIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="181">I like not fair terms and a villain's mind.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech46"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="182">Come on: in this there can be no dismay;</a><br/>
<a NAME="183">My ships come home a month before the day.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
