<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE III. A room in the castle.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter KING CLAUDIUS, ROSENCRANTZ, and GUILDENSTERN</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>KING CLAUDIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">I like him not, nor stands it safe with us</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">To let his madness range. Therefore prepare you;</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">I your commission will forthwith dispatch,</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">And he to England shall along with you:</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">The terms of our estate may not endure</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">Hazard so dangerous as doth hourly grow</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Out of his lunacies.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>GUILDENSTERN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="8">We will ourselves provide:</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Most holy and religious fear it is</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">To keep those many many bodies safe</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">That live and feed upon your majesty.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>ROSENCRANTZ</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="12">The single and peculiar life is bound,</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">With all the strength and armour of the mind,</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">To keep itself from noyance; but much more</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">That spirit upon whose weal depend and rest</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">The lives of many. The cease of majesty</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">Dies not alone; but, like a gulf, doth draw</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">What's near it with it: it is a massy wheel,</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">Fix'd on the summit of the highest mount,</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">To whose huge spokes ten thousand lesser things</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">Are mortised and adjoin'd; which, when it falls,</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">Each small annexment, petty consequence,</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Attends the boisterous ruin. Never alone</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">Did the king sigh, but with a general groan.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>KING CLAUDIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="25">Arm you, I pray you, to this speedy voyage;</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">For we will fetters put upon this fear,</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">Which now goes too free-footed.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>ROSENCRANTZ</b></a>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>GUILDENSTERN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="28">We will haste us.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt ROSENCRANTZ and GUILDENSTERN</i></p>
<p><i>Enter POLONIUS</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>LORD POLONIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="29">My lord, he's going to his mother's closet:</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Behind the arras I'll convey myself,</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">To hear the process; and warrant she'll tax him home:</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">And, as you said, and wisely was it said,</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">'Tis meet that some more audience than a mother,</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">Since nature makes them partial, should o'erhear</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">The speech, of vantage. Fare you well, my liege:</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">I'll call upon you ere you go to bed,</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">And tell you what I know.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>KING CLAUDIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="38">Thanks, dear my lord.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit POLONIUS</i></p>
<a NAME="39">O, my offence is rank it smells to heaven;</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">It hath the primal eldest curse upon't,</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">A brother's murder. Pray can I not,</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">Though inclination be as sharp as will:</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">My stronger guilt defeats my strong intent;</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">And, like a man to double business bound,</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">I stand in pause where I shall first begin,</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">And both neglect. What if this cursed hand</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">Were thicker than itself with brother's blood,</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">Is there not rain enough in the sweet heavens</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">To wash it white as snow? Whereto serves mercy</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">But to confront the visage of offence?</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">And what's in prayer but this two-fold force,</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">To be forestalled ere we come to fall,</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">Or pardon'd being down? Then I'll look up;</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">My fault is past. But, O, what form of prayer</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">Can serve my turn? 'Forgive me my foul murder'?</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">That cannot be; since I am still possess'd</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">Of those effects for which I did the murder,</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">My crown, mine own ambition and my queen.</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">May one be pardon'd and retain the offence?</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">In the corrupted currents of this world</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">Offence's gilded hand may shove by justice,</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">And oft 'tis seen the wicked prize itself</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">Buys out the law: but 'tis not so above;</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">There is no shuffling, there the action lies</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">In his true nature; and we ourselves compell'd,</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">Even to the teeth and forehead of our faults,</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">To give in evidence. What then? what rests?</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">Try what repentance can: what can it not?</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">Yet what can it when one can not repent?</a><br/>
<a NAME="70">O wretched state! O bosom black as death!</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">O limed soul, that, struggling to be free,</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">Art more engaged! Help, angels! Make assay!</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">Bow, stubborn knees; and, heart with strings of steel,</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">Be soft as sinews of the newborn babe!</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">All may be well.</a><br/>
<p><i>Retires and kneels</i></p>
<p><i>Enter HAMLET</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>HAMLET</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="76">Now might I do it pat, now he is praying;</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">And now I'll do't. And so he goes to heaven;</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">And so am I revenged. That would be scann'd:</a><br/>
<a NAME="79">A villain kills my father; and for that,</a><br/>
<a NAME="80">I, his sole son, do this same villain send</a><br/>
<a NAME="81">To heaven.</a><br/>
<a NAME="82">O, this is hire and salary, not revenge.</a><br/>
<a NAME="83">He took my father grossly, full of bread;</a><br/>
<a NAME="84">With all his crimes broad blown, as flush as May;</a><br/>
<a NAME="85">And how his audit stands who knows save heaven?</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">But in our circumstance and course of thought,</a><br/>
<a NAME="87">'Tis heavy with him: and am I then revenged,</a><br/>
<a NAME="88">To take him in the purging of his soul,</a><br/>
<a NAME="89">When he is fit and season'd for his passage?</a><br/>
<a NAME="90">No!</a><br/>
<a NAME="91">Up, sword; and know thou a more horrid hent:</a><br/>
<a NAME="92">When he is drunk asleep, or in his rage,</a><br/>
<a NAME="93">Or in the incestuous pleasure of his bed;</a><br/>
<a NAME="94">At gaming, swearing, or about some act</a><br/>
<a NAME="95">That has no relish of salvation in't;</a><br/>
<a NAME="96">Then trip him, that his heels may kick at heaven,</a><br/>
<a NAME="97">And that his soul may be as damn'd and black</a><br/>
<a NAME="98">As hell, whereto it goes. My mother stays:</a><br/>
<a NAME="99">This physic but prolongs thy sickly days.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>KING CLAUDIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="100">[Rising]  My words fly up, my thoughts remain below:</a><br/>
<a NAME="101">Words without thoughts never to heaven go.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
