<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. DUKE ORSINO's palace.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter DUKE ORSINO, CURIO, and other Lords; Musicians attending</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>DUKE ORSINO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">If music be the food of love, play on;</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">Give me excess of it, that, surfeiting,</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">The appetite may sicken, and so die.</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">That strain again! it had a dying fall:</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">O, it came o'er my ear like the sweet sound,</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">That breathes upon a bank of violets,</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Stealing and giving odour! Enough; no more:</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">'Tis not so sweet now as it was before.</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">O spirit of love! how quick and fresh art thou,</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">That, notwithstanding thy capacity</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Receiveth as the sea, nought enters there,</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">Of what validity and pitch soe'er,</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">But falls into abatement and low price,</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">Even in a minute: so full of shapes is fancy</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">That it alone is high fantastical.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>CURIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="16">Will you go hunt, my lord?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>DUKE ORSINO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="17">What, Curio?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>CURIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="18">The hart.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>DUKE ORSINO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="19">        Why, so I do, the noblest that I have:</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">O, when mine eyes did see Olivia first,</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">Methought she purged the air of pestilence!</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">That instant was I turn'd into a hart;</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">And my desires, like fell and cruel hounds,</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">E'er since pursue me.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter VALENTINE</i></p>
<a NAME="25">How now! what news from her?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>VALENTINE</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="26">So please my lord, I might not be admitted;</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">But from her handmaid do return this answer:</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">The element itself, till seven years' heat,</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Shall not behold her face at ample view;</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">But, like a cloistress, she will veiled walk</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">And water once a day her chamber round</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">With eye-offending brine: all this to season</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">A brother's dead love, which she would keep fresh</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">And lasting in her sad remembrance.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>DUKE ORSINO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="35">O, she that hath a heart of that fine frame</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">To pay this debt of love but to a brother,</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">How will she love, when the rich golden shaft</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">Hath kill'd the flock of all affections else</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">That live in her; when liver, brain and heart,</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">These sovereign thrones, are all supplied, and fill'd</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">Her sweet perfections with one self king!</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">Away before me to sweet beds of flowers:</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">Love-thoughts lie rich when canopied with bowers.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
