<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. The sea-coast.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter ANTONIO and SEBASTIAN</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Will you stay no longer? nor will you not that I go with you?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>SEBASTIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="2">By your patience, no. My stars shine darkly over</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">me: the malignancy of my fate might perhaps</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">distemper yours; therefore I shall crave of you your</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">leave that I may bear my evils alone: it were a bad</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">recompense for your love, to lay any of them on you.</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">ANTONIO: Let me yet know of you whither you are bound.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>SEBASTIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="8">No, sooth, sir: my determinate voyage is mere</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">extravagancy. But I perceive in you so excellent a</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">touch of modesty, that you will not extort from me</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">what I am willing to keep in; therefore it charges</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">me in manners the rather to express myself. You</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">must know of me then, Antonio, my name is Sebastian,</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">which I called Roderigo. My father was that</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">Sebastian of Messaline, whom I know you have heard</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">of. He left behind him myself and a sister, both</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">born in an hour: if the heavens had been pleased,</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">would we had so ended! but you, sir, altered that;</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">for some hour before you took me from the breach of</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">the sea was my sister drowned.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="21">Alas the day!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>SEBASTIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="22">A lady, sir, though it was said she much resembled</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">me, was yet of many accounted beautiful: but,</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">though I could not with such estimable wonder</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">overfar believe that, yet thus far I will boldly</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">publish her; she bore a mind that envy could not but</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">call fair. She is drowned already, sir, with salt</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">water, though I seem to drown her remembrance again with more.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="29">Pardon me, sir, your bad entertainment.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>SEBASTIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="30">O good Antonio, forgive me your trouble.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="31">If you will not murder me for my love, let me be</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">your servant.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>SEBASTIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="33">If you will not undo what you have done, that is,</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">kill him whom you have recovered, desire it not.</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">Fare ye well at once: my bosom is full of kindness,</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">and I am yet so near the manners of my mother, that</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">upon the least occasion more mine eyes will tell</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">tales of me. I am bound to the Count Orsino's court: farewell.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>ANTONIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="39">The gentleness of all the gods go with thee!</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">I have many enemies in Orsino's court,</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">Else would I very shortly see thee there.</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">But, come what may, I do adore thee so,</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">That danger shall seem sport, and I will go.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
