<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE II. OLIVIA's house.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter SIR TOBY BELCH, SIR ANDREW, and FABIAN</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>SIR ANDREW</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">No, faith, I'll not stay a jot longer.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>SIR TOBY BELCH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="2">Thy reason, dear venom, give thy reason.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>FABIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="3">You must needs yield your reason, Sir Andrew.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>SIR ANDREW</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="4">Marry, I saw your niece do more favours to the</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">count's serving-man than ever she bestowed upon me;</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">I saw't i' the orchard.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>SIR TOBY BELCH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="7">Did she see thee the while, old boy? tell me that.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>SIR ANDREW</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="8">As plain as I see you now.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>FABIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="9">This was a great argument of love in her toward you.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>SIR ANDREW</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="10">'Slight, will you make an ass o' me?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>FABIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="11">I will prove it legitimate, sir, upon the oaths of</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">judgment and reason.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>SIR TOBY BELCH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="13">And they have been grand-jury-men since before Noah</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">was a sailor.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>FABIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="15">She did show favour to the youth in your sight only</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">to exasperate you, to awake your dormouse valour, to</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">put fire in your heart and brimstone in your liver.</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">You should then have accosted her; and with some</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">excellent jests, fire-new from the mint, you should</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">have banged the youth into dumbness. This was</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">looked for at your hand, and this was balked: the</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">double gilt of this opportunity you let time wash</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">off, and you are now sailed into the north of my</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">lady's opinion; where you will hang like an icicle</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">on a Dutchman's beard, unless you do redeem it by</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">some laudable attempt either of valour or policy.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>SIR ANDREW</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="27">An't be any way, it must be with valour; for policy</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">I hate: I had as lief be a Brownist as a</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">politician.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>SIR TOBY BELCH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="30">Why, then, build me thy fortunes upon the basis of</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">valour. Challenge me the count's youth to fight</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">with him; hurt him in eleven places: my niece shall</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">take note of it; and assure thyself, there is no</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">love-broker in the world can more prevail in man's</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">commendation with woman than report of valour.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>FABIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="36">There is no way but this, Sir Andrew.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>SIR ANDREW</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="37">Will either of you bear me a challenge to him?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>SIR TOBY BELCH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="38">Go, write it in a martial hand; be curst and brief;</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">it is no matter how witty, so it be eloquent and fun</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">of invention: taunt him with the licence of ink:</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">if thou thou'st him some thrice, it shall not be</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">amiss; and as many lies as will lie in thy sheet of</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">paper, although the sheet were big enough for the</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">bed of Ware in England, set 'em down: go, about it.</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">Let there be gall enough in thy ink, though thou</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">write with a goose-pen, no matter: about it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>SIR ANDREW</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="47">Where shall I find you?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>SIR TOBY BELCH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="48">We'll call thee at the cubiculo: go.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit SIR ANDREW</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>FABIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="49">This is a dear manikin to you, Sir Toby.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>SIR TOBY BELCH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="50">I have been dear to him, lad, some two thousand</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">strong, or so.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>FABIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="52">We shall have a rare letter from him: but you'll</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">not deliver't?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>SIR TOBY BELCH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="54">Never trust me, then; and by all means stir on the</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">youth to an answer. I think oxen and wainropes</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">cannot hale them together. For Andrew, if he were</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">opened, and you find so much blood in his liver as</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">will clog the foot of a flea, I'll eat the rest of</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">the anatomy.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>FABIAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="60">And his opposite, the youth, bears in his visage no</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">great presage of cruelty.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter MARIA</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech24"><b>SIR TOBY BELCH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="62">Look, where the youngest wren of nine comes.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech25"><b>MARIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="63">If you desire the spleen, and will laugh yourself</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">into stitches, follow me. Yond gull Malvolio is</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">turned heathen, a very renegado; for there is no</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">Christian, that means to be saved by believing</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">rightly, can ever believe such impossible passages</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">of grossness. He's in yellow stockings.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech26"><b>SIR TOBY BELCH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="69">And cross-gartered?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech27"><b>MARIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="70">Most villanously; like a pedant that keeps a school</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">i' the church. I have dogged him, like his</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">murderer. He does obey every point of the letter</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">that I dropped to betray him: he does smile his</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">face into more lines than is in the new map with the</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">augmentation of the Indies: you have not seen such</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">a thing as 'tis. I can hardly forbear hurling things</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">at him. I know my lady will strike him: if she do,</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">he'll smile and take't for a great favour.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech28"><b>SIR TOBY BELCH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="79">Come, bring us, bring us where he is.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
