<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE II. A street.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter VIOLA, MALVOLIO following</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>MALVOLIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Were not you even now with the Countess Olivia?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>VIOLA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="2">Even now, sir; on a moderate pace I have since</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">arrived but hither.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>MALVOLIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="4">She returns this ring to you, sir: you might have</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">saved me my pains, to have taken it away yourself.</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">She adds, moreover, that you should put your lord</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">into a desperate assurance she will none of him:</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">and one thing more, that you be never so hardy to</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">come again in his affairs, unless it be to report</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">your lord's taking of this. Receive it so.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>VIOLA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="11">She took the ring of me: I'll none of it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>MALVOLIO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="12">Come, sir, you peevishly threw it to her; and her</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">will is, it should be so returned: if it be worth</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">stooping for, there it lies in your eye; if not, be</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">it his that finds it.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>VIOLA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="16">I left no ring with her: what means this lady?</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">Fortune forbid my outside have not charm'd her!</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">She made good view of me; indeed, so much,</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">That sure methought her eyes had lost her tongue,</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">For she did speak in starts distractedly.</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">She loves me, sure; the cunning of her passion</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">Invites me in this churlish messenger.</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">None of my lord's ring! why, he sent her none.</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">I am the man: if it be so, as 'tis,</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">Poor lady, she were better love a dream.</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">Disguise, I see, thou art a wickedness,</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">Wherein the pregnant enemy does much.</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">How easy is it for the proper-false</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">In women's waxen hearts to set their forms!</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Alas, our frailty is the cause, not we!</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">For such as we are made of, such we be.</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">How will this fadge? my master loves her dearly;</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">And I, poor monster, fond as much on him;</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">And she, mistaken, seems to dote on me.</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">What will become of this? As I am man,</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">My state is desperate for my master's love;</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">As I am woman,--now alas the day!--</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">What thriftless sighs shall poor Olivia breathe!</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">O time! thou must untangle this, not I;</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">It is too hard a knot for me to untie!</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
