<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. Before an alehouse on a heath.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter Hostess and SLY</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>SLY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">I'll pheeze you, in faith.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>Hostess</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="2">A pair of stocks, you rogue!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>SLY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="3">Ye are a baggage: the Slys are no rogues; look in</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">the chronicles; we came in with Richard Conqueror.</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Therefore paucas pallabris; let the world slide: sessa!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>Hostess</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="6">You will not pay for the glasses you have burst?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>SLY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="7">No, not a denier. Go by, Jeronimy: go to thy cold</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">bed, and warm thee.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>Hostess</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="9">I know my remedy; I must go fetch the</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">third--borough.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>SLY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="11">Third, or fourth, or fifth borough, I'll answer him</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">by law: I'll not budge an inch, boy: let him come,</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">and kindly.</a><br/>
<p><i>Falls asleep</i></p>
<p><i>Horns winded. Enter a Lord from hunting, with his train</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="14">Huntsman, I charge thee, tender well my hounds:</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">Brach Merriman, the poor cur is emboss'd;</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">And couple Clowder with the deep--mouth'd brach.</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">Saw'st thou not, boy, how Silver made it good</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">At the hedge-corner, in the coldest fault?</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">I would not lose the dog for twenty pound.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>First Huntsman</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="20">Why, Belman is as good as he, my lord;</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">He cried upon it at the merest loss</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">And twice to-day pick'd out the dullest scent:</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Trust me, I take him for the better dog.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="24">Thou art a fool: if Echo were as fleet,</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">I would esteem him worth a dozen such.</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">But sup them well and look unto them all:</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">To-morrow I intend to hunt again.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>First Huntsman</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="28">I will, my lord.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="29">What's here? one dead, or drunk? See, doth he breathe?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>Second Huntsman</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="30">He breathes, my lord. Were he not warm'd with ale,</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">This were a bed but cold to sleep so soundly.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="32">O monstrous beast! how like a swine he lies!</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">Grim death, how foul and loathsome is thine image!</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">Sirs, I will practise on this drunken man.</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">What think you, if he were convey'd to bed,</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">Wrapp'd in sweet clothes, rings put upon his fingers,</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">A most delicious banquet by his bed,</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">And brave attendants near him when he wakes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">Would not the beggar then forget himself?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>First Huntsman</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="40">Believe me, lord, I think he cannot choose.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>Second Huntsman</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="41">It would seem strange unto him when he waked.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="42">Even as a flattering dream or worthless fancy.</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">Then take him up and manage well the jest:</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">Carry him gently to my fairest chamber</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">And hang it round with all my wanton pictures:</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">Balm his foul head in warm distilled waters</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">And burn sweet wood to make the lodging sweet:</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">Procure me music ready when he wakes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">To make a dulcet and a heavenly sound;</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">And if he chance to speak, be ready straight</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">And with a low submissive reverence</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">Say 'What is it your honour will command?'</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">Let one attend him with a silver basin</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">Full of rose-water and bestrew'd with flowers,</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">Another bear the ewer, the third a diaper,</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">And say 'Will't please your lordship cool your hands?'</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">Some one be ready with a costly suit</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">And ask him what apparel he will wear;</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">Another tell him of his hounds and horse,</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">And that his lady mourns at his disease:</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">Persuade him that he hath been lunatic;</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">And when he says he is, say that he dreams,</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">For he is nothing but a mighty lord.</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">This do and do it kindly, gentle sirs:</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">It will be pastime passing excellent,</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">If it be husbanded with modesty.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>First Huntsman</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="67">My lord, I warrant you we will play our part,</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">As he shall think by our true diligence</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">He is no less than what we say he is.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="70">Take him up gently and to bed with him;</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">And each one to his office when he wakes.</a><br/>
<p><i>Some bear out SLY. A trumpet sounds</i></p>
<a NAME="72">Sirrah, go see what trumpet 'tis that sounds:</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit Servingman</i></p>
<a NAME="73">Belike, some noble gentleman that means,</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">Travelling some journey, to repose him here.</a><br/>
<p><i>Re-enter Servingman</i></p>
<a NAME="75">How now! who is it?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>Servant</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="76">An't please your honour, players</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">That offer service to your lordship.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="78">Bid them come near.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter Players</i></p>
<a NAME="79">Now, fellows, you are welcome.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>Players</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="80">We thank your honour.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="81">Do you intend to stay with me tonight?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech24"><b>A Player</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="82">So please your lordship to accept our duty.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech25"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="83">With all my heart. This fellow I remember,</a><br/>
<a NAME="84">Since once he play'd a farmer's eldest son:</a><br/>
<a NAME="85">'Twas where you woo'd the gentlewoman so well:</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">I have forgot your name; but, sure, that part</a><br/>
<a NAME="87">Was aptly fitted and naturally perform'd.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech26"><b>A Player</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="88">I think 'twas Soto that your honour means.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech27"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="89">'Tis very true: thou didst it excellent.</a><br/>
<a NAME="90">Well, you are come to me in a happy time;</a><br/>
<a NAME="91">The rather for I have some sport in hand</a><br/>
<a NAME="92">Wherein your cunning can assist me much.</a><br/>
<a NAME="93">There is a lord will hear you play to-night:</a><br/>
<a NAME="94">But I am doubtful of your modesties;</a><br/>
<a NAME="95">Lest over-eyeing of his odd behavior,--</a><br/>
<a NAME="96">For yet his honour never heard a play--</a><br/>
<a NAME="97">You break into some merry passion</a><br/>
<a NAME="98">And so offend him; for I tell you, sirs,</a><br/>
<a NAME="99">If you should smile he grows impatient.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech28"><b>A Player</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="100">Fear not, my lord: we can contain ourselves,</a><br/>
<a NAME="101">Were he the veriest antic in the world.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech29"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="102">Go, sirrah, take them to the buttery,</a><br/>
<a NAME="103">And give them friendly welcome every one:</a><br/>
<a NAME="104">Let them want nothing that my house affords.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit one with the Players</i></p>
<a NAME="105">Sirrah, go you to Barthol'mew my page,</a><br/>
<a NAME="106">And see him dress'd in all suits like a lady:</a><br/>
<a NAME="107">That done, conduct him to the drunkard's chamber;</a><br/>
<a NAME="108">And call him 'madam,' do him obeisance.</a><br/>
<a NAME="109">Tell him from me, as he will win my love,</a><br/>
<a NAME="110">He bear himself with honourable action,</a><br/>
<a NAME="111">Such as he hath observed in noble ladies</a><br/>
<a NAME="112">Unto their lords, by them accomplished:</a><br/>
<a NAME="113">Such duty to the drunkard let him do</a><br/>
<a NAME="114">With soft low tongue and lowly courtesy,</a><br/>
<a NAME="115">And say 'What is't your honour will command,</a><br/>
<a NAME="116">Wherein your lady and your humble wife</a><br/>
<a NAME="117">May show her duty and make known her love?'</a><br/>
<a NAME="118">And then with kind embracements, tempting kisses,</a><br/>
<a NAME="119">And with declining head into his bosom,</a><br/>
<a NAME="120">Bid him shed tears, as being overjoy'd</a><br/>
<a NAME="121">To see her noble lord restored to health,</a><br/>
<a NAME="122">Who for this seven years hath esteem'd him</a><br/>
<a NAME="123">No better than a poor and loathsome beggar:</a><br/>
<a NAME="124">And if the boy have not a woman's gift</a><br/>
<a NAME="125">To rain a shower of commanded tears,</a><br/>
<a NAME="126">An onion will do well for such a shift,</a><br/>
<a NAME="127">Which in a napkin being close convey'd</a><br/>
<a NAME="128">Shall in despite enforce a watery eye.</a><br/>
<a NAME="129">See this dispatch'd with all the haste thou canst:</a><br/>
<a NAME="130">Anon I'll give thee more instructions.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit a Servingman</i></p>
<a NAME="131">I know the boy will well usurp the grace,</a><br/>
<a NAME="132">Voice, gait and action of a gentlewoman:</a><br/>
<a NAME="133">I long to hear him call the drunkard husband,</a><br/>
<a NAME="134">And how my men will stay themselves from laughter</a><br/>
<a NAME="135">When they do homage to this simple peasant.</a><br/>
<a NAME="136">I'll in to counsel them; haply my presence</a><br/>
<a NAME="137">May well abate the over-merry spleen</a><br/>
<a NAME="138">Which otherwise would grow into extremes.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
