<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE III. Gloucester's castle.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter GLOUCESTER and EDMUND</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>GLOUCESTER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Alack, alack, Edmund, I like not this unnatural</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">dealing. When I desire their leave that I might</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">pity him, they took from me the use of mine own</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">house; charged me, on pain of their perpetual</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">displeasure, neither to speak of him, entreat for</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">him, nor any way sustain him.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>EDMUND</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="7">Most savage and unnatural!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>GLOUCESTER</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="8">Go to; say you nothing. There's a division betwixt</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">the dukes; and a worse matter than that: I have</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">received a letter this night; 'tis dangerous to be</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">spoken; I have locked the letter in my closet:</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">these injuries the king now bears will be revenged</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">home; there's part of a power already footed: we</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">must incline to the king. I will seek him, and</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">privily relieve him: go you and maintain talk with</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">the duke, that my charity be not of him perceived:</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">if he ask for me. I am ill, and gone to bed.</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">Though I die for it, as no less is threatened me,</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">the king my old master must be relieved. There is</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">some strange thing toward, Edmund; pray you, be careful.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>EDMUND</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="21">This courtesy, forbid thee, shall the duke</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">Instantly know; and of that letter too:</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">This seems a fair deserving, and must draw me</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">That which my father loses; no less than all:</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">The younger rises when the old doth fall.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
