<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE XII. Another part of the same.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter MARK ANTONY and SCARUS</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>MARK ANTONY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Yet they are not join'd: where yond pine</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">does stand,</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">I shall discover all: I'll bring thee word</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">Straight, how 'tis like to go.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>SCARUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="5">Swallows have built</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">In Cleopatra's sails their nests: the augurers</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Say they know not, they cannot tell; look grimly,</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">And dare not speak their knowledge. Antony</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Is valiant, and dejected; and, by starts,</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">His fretted fortunes give him hope, and fear,</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Of what he has, and has not.</a><br/>
<p><i>Alarum afar off, as at a sea-fight</i></p>
<p><i>Re-enter MARK ANTONY</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>MARK ANTONY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="12">All is lost;</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">This foul Egyptian hath betrayed me:</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">My fleet hath yielded to the foe; and yonder</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">They cast their caps up and carouse together</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">Like friends long lost. Triple-turn'd whore!</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">'tis thou</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">Hast sold me to this novice; and my heart</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">Makes only wars on thee. Bid them all fly;</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">For when I am revenged upon my charm,</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">I have done all. Bid them all fly; begone.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit SCARUS</i></p>
<a NAME="22">O sun, thy uprise shall I see no more:</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Fortune and Antony part here; even here</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">Do we shake hands. All come to this? The hearts</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">That spaniel'd me at heels, to whom I gave</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">Their wishes, do discandy, melt their sweets</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">On blossoming Caesar; and this pine is bark'd,</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">That overtopp'd them all. Betray'd I am:</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">O this false soul of Egypt! this grave charm,--</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Whose eye beck'd forth my wars, and call'd them home;</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">Whose bosom was my crownet, my chief end,--</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">Like a right gipsy, hath, at fast and loose,</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">Beguiled me to the very heart of loss.</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">What, Eros, Eros!</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter CLEOPATRA</i></p>
<a NAME="35">Ah, thou spell! Avaunt!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>CLEOPATRA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="36">Why is my lord enraged against his love?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>MARK ANTONY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="37">Vanish, or I shall give thee thy deserving,</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">And blemish Caesar's triumph. Let him take thee,</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">And hoist thee up to the shouting plebeians:</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">Follow his chariot, like the greatest spot</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">Of all thy sex; most monster-like, be shown</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">For poor'st diminutives, for doits; and let</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">Patient Octavia plough thy visage up</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">With her prepared nails.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit CLEOPATRA</i></p>
<a NAME="45">'Tis well thou'rt gone,</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">If it be well to live; but better 'twere</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">Thou fell'st into my fury, for one death</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">Might have prevented many. Eros, ho!</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">The shirt of Nessus is upon me: teach me,</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">Alcides, thou mine ancestor, thy rage:</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">Let me lodge Lichas on the horns o' the moon;</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">And with those hands, that grasp'd the heaviest club,</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">Subdue my worthiest self. The witch shall die:</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">To the young Roman boy she hath sold me, and I fall</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">Under this plot; she dies for't. Eros, ho!</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
