<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. A plain in Syria.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter VENTIDIUS as it were in triumph, with SILIUS,  and other Romans, Officers, and Soldiers; the dead body of PACORUS borne before him</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>VENTIDIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Now, darting Parthia, art thou struck; and now</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">Pleased fortune does of Marcus Crassus' death</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">Make me revenger. Bear the king's son's body</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">Before our army. Thy Pacorus, Orodes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Pays this for Marcus Crassus.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>SILIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="6">Noble Ventidius,</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Whilst yet with Parthian blood thy sword is warm,</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">The fugitive Parthians follow; spur through Media,</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Mesopotamia, and the shelters whither</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">The routed fly: so thy grand captain Antony</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Shall set thee on triumphant chariots and</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">Put garlands on thy head.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>VENTIDIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="13">O Silius, Silius,</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">I have done enough; a lower place, note well,</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">May make too great an act: for learn this, Silius;</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">Better to leave undone, than by our deed</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">Acquire too high a fame when him we serve's away.</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">Caesar and Antony have ever won</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">More in their officer than person: Sossius,</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">One of my place in Syria, his lieutenant,</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">For quick accumulation of renown,</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">Which he achieved by the minute, lost his favour.</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Who does i' the wars more than his captain can</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">Becomes his captain's captain: and ambition,</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">The soldier's virtue, rather makes choice of loss,</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">Than gain which darkens him.</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">I could do more to do Antonius good,</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">But 'twould offend him; and in his offence</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Should my performance perish.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>SILIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="30">Thou hast, Ventidius,</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">that</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">Without the which a soldier, and his sword,</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">Grants scarce distinction. Thou wilt write to Antony!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>VENTIDIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="34">I'll humbly signify what in his name,</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">That magical word of war, we have effected;</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">How, with his banners and his well-paid ranks,</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">The ne'er-yet-beaten horse of Parthia</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">We have jaded out o' the field.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>SILIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="39">Where is he now?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>VENTIDIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="40">He purposeth to Athens: whither, with what haste</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">The weight we must convey with's will permit,</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">We shall appear before him. On there; pass along!</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
