<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. Alexandria. A room in CLEOPATRA's palace.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter DEMETRIUS and PHILO</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>PHILO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Nay, but this dotage of our general's</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">O'erflows the measure: those his goodly eyes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">That o'er the files and musters of the war</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">Have glow'd like plated Mars, now bend, now turn,</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">The office and devotion of their view</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">Upon a tawny front: his captain's heart,</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Which in the scuffles of great fights hath burst</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">The buckles on his breast, reneges all temper,</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">And is become the bellows and the fan</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">To cool a gipsy's lust.</a><br/>
<p><i>Flourish. Enter ANTONY, CLEOPATRA, her Ladies, the Train, with Eunuchs fanning her</i></p>
<a NAME="11">Look, where they come:</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">Take but good note, and you shall see in him.</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">The triple pillar of the world transform'd</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">Into a strumpet's fool: behold and see.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>CLEOPATRA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="15">If it be love indeed, tell me how much.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>MARK ANTONY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="16">There's beggary in the love that can be reckon'd.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>CLEOPATRA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="17">I'll set a bourn how far to be beloved.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>MARK ANTONY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="18">Then must thou needs find out new heaven, new earth.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter an Attendant</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>Attendant</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="19">News, my good lord, from Rome.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>MARK ANTONY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="20">Grates me: the sum.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>CLEOPATRA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="21">Nay, hear them, Antony:</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">Fulvia perchance is angry; or, who knows</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">If the scarce-bearded Caesar have not sent</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">His powerful mandate to you, 'Do this, or this;</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">Take in that kingdom, and enfranchise that;</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">Perform 't, or else we damn thee.'</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>MARK ANTONY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="27">How, my love!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>CLEOPATRA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="28">Perchance! nay, and most like:</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">You must not stay here longer, your dismission</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Is come from Caesar; therefore hear it, Antony.</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">Where's Fulvia's process? Caesar's I would say? both?</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">Call in the messengers. As I am Egypt's queen,</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">Thou blushest, Antony; and that blood of thine</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">Is Caesar's homager: else so thy cheek pays shame</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">When shrill-tongued Fulvia scolds. The messengers!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>MARK ANTONY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="36">Let Rome in Tiber melt, and the wide arch</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">Of the ranged empire fall! Here is my space.</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">Kingdoms are clay: our dungy earth alike</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">Feeds beast as man: the nobleness of life</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">Is to do thus; when such a mutual pair</a><br/>
<p><i>Embracing</i></p>
<a NAME="41">And such a twain can do't, in which I bind,</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">On pain of punishment, the world to weet</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">We stand up peerless.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>CLEOPATRA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="44">Excellent falsehood!</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">Why did he marry Fulvia, and not love her?</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">I'll seem the fool I am not; Antony</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">Will be himself.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>MARK ANTONY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="48">                  But stirr'd by Cleopatra.</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">Now, for the love of Love and her soft hours,</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">Let's not confound the time with conference harsh:</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">There's not a minute of our lives should stretch</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">Without some pleasure now. What sport tonight?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>CLEOPATRA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="53">Hear the ambassadors.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>MARK ANTONY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="54">Fie, wrangling queen!</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">Whom every thing becomes, to chide, to laugh,</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">To weep; whose every passion fully strives</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">To make itself, in thee, fair and admired!</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">No messenger, but thine; and all alone</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">To-night we'll wander through the streets and note</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">The qualities of people. Come, my queen;</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">Last night you did desire it: speak not to us.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt MARK ANTONY and CLEOPATRA with their train</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>DEMETRIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="62">Is Caesar with Antonius prized so slight?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>PHILO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="63">Sir, sometimes, when he is not Antony,</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">He comes too short of that great property</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">Which still should go with Antony.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>DEMETRIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="66">I am full sorry</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">That he approves the common liar, who</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">Thus speaks of him at Rome: but I will hope</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">Of better deeds to-morrow. Rest you happy!</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
