<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE IV. Forres. The palace.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Flourish. Enter DUNCAN, MALCOLM, DONALBAIN, LENNOX, and Attendants</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>DUNCAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Is execution done on Cawdor? Are not</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">Those in commission yet return'd?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>MALCOLM</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="3">My liege,</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">They are not yet come back. But I have spoke</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">With one that saw him die: who did report</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">That very frankly he confess'd his treasons,</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Implored your highness' pardon and set forth</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">A deep repentance: nothing in his life</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Became him like the leaving it; he died</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">As one that had been studied in his death</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">To throw away the dearest thing he owed,</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">As 'twere a careless trifle.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>DUNCAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="13">There's no art</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">To find the mind's construction in the face:</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">He was a gentleman on whom I built</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">An absolute trust.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter MACBETH, BANQUO, ROSS, and ANGUS</i></p>
<a NAME="17">O worthiest cousin!</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">The sin of my ingratitude even now</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">Was heavy on me: thou art so far before</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">That swiftest wing of recompense is slow</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">To overtake thee. Would thou hadst less deserved,</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">That the proportion both of thanks and payment</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Might have been mine! only I have left to say,</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">More is thy due than more than all can pay.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="25">The service and the loyalty I owe,</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">In doing it, pays itself. Your highness' part</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">Is to receive our duties; and our duties</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">Are to your throne and state children and servants,</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Which do but what they should, by doing every thing</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Safe toward your love and honour.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>DUNCAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="31">Welcome hither:</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">I have begun to plant thee, and will labour</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">To make thee full of growing. Noble Banquo,</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">That hast no less deserved, nor must be known</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">No less to have done so, let me enfold thee</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">And hold thee to my heart.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>BANQUO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="37">There if I grow,</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">The harvest is your own.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>DUNCAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="39">My plenteous joys,</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">Wanton in fulness, seek to hide themselves</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">In drops of sorrow. Sons, kinsmen, thanes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">And you whose places are the nearest, know</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">We will establish our estate upon</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">Our eldest, Malcolm, whom we name hereafter</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">The Prince of Cumberland; which honour must</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">Not unaccompanied invest him only,</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">But signs of nobleness, like stars, shall shine</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">On all deservers. From hence to Inverness,</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">And bind us further to you.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="50">The rest is labour, which is not used for you:</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">I'll be myself the harbinger and make joyful</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">The hearing of my wife with your approach;</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">So humbly take my leave.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>DUNCAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="54">My worthy Cawdor!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="55">[Aside]  The Prince of Cumberland! that is a step</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">On which I must fall down, or else o'erleap,</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">For in my way it lies. Stars, hide your fires;</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">Let not light see my black and deep desires:</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">The eye wink at the hand; yet let that be,</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">Which the eye fears, when it is done, to see.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>DUNCAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="61">True, worthy Banquo; he is full so valiant,</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">And in his commendations I am fed;</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">It is a banquet to me. Let's after him,</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">Whose care is gone before to bid us welcome:</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">It is a peerless kinsman.</a><br/>
<p><i>Flourish. Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
