<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE VII. Macbeth's castle.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Hautboys and torches. Enter a Sewer, and divers  Servants with dishes and service, and pass over the stage. Then enter MACBETH</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">If it were done when 'tis done, then 'twere well</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">It were done quickly: if the assassination</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">Could trammel up the consequence, and catch</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">With his surcease success; that but this blow</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Might be the be-all and the end-all here,</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">But here, upon this bank and shoal of time,</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">We'ld jump the life to come. But in these cases</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">We still have judgment here; that we but teach</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Bloody instructions, which, being taught, return</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">To plague the inventor: this even-handed justice</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Commends the ingredients of our poison'd chalice</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">To our own lips. He's here in double trust;</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">First, as I am his kinsman and his subject,</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">Strong both against the deed; then, as his host,</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">Who should against his murderer shut the door,</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">Not bear the knife myself. Besides, this Duncan</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">Hath borne his faculties so meek, hath been</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">So clear in his great office, that his virtues</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">Will plead like angels, trumpet-tongued, against</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">The deep damnation of his taking-off;</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">And pity, like a naked new-born babe,</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">Striding the blast, or heaven's cherubim, horsed</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Upon the sightless couriers of the air,</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">Shall blow the horrid deed in every eye,</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">That tears shall drown the wind. I have no spur</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">To prick the sides of my intent, but only</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">Vaulting ambition, which o'erleaps itself</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">And falls on the other.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter LADY MACBETH</i></p>
<a NAME="29">How now! what news?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>LADY MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="30">He has almost supp'd: why have you left the chamber?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="31">Hath he ask'd for me?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>LADY MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="32">Know you not he has?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="33">We will proceed no further in this business:</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">He hath honour'd me of late; and I have bought</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">Golden opinions from all sorts of people,</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">Which would be worn now in their newest gloss,</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">Not cast aside so soon.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>LADY MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="38">Was the hope drunk</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">Wherein you dress'd yourself? hath it slept since?</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">And wakes it now, to look so green and pale</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">At what it did so freely? From this time</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">Such I account thy love. Art thou afeard</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">To be the same in thine own act and valour</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">As thou art in desire? Wouldst thou have that</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">Which thou esteem'st the ornament of life,</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">And live a coward in thine own esteem,</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">Letting 'I dare not' wait upon 'I would,'</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">Like the poor cat i' the adage?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="49">Prithee, peace:</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">I dare do all that may become a man;</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">Who dares do more is none.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>LADY MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="52">What beast was't, then,</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">That made you break this enterprise to me?</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">When you durst do it, then you were a man;</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">And, to be more than what you were, you would</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">Be so much more the man. Nor time nor place</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">Did then adhere, and yet you would make both:</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">They have made themselves, and that their fitness now</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">Does unmake you. I have given suck, and know</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">How tender 'tis to love the babe that milks me:</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">I would, while it was smiling in my face,</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">Have pluck'd my nipple from his boneless gums,</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">And dash'd the brains out, had I so sworn as you</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">Have done to this.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="65">                  If we should fail?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>LADY MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="66">We fail!</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">But screw your courage to the sticking-place,</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">And we'll not fail. When Duncan is asleep--</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">Whereto the rather shall his day's hard journey</a><br/>
<a NAME="70">Soundly invite him--his two chamberlains</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">Will I with wine and wassail so convince</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">That memory, the warder of the brain,</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">Shall be a fume, and the receipt of reason</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">A limbeck only: when in swinish sleep</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">Their drenched natures lie as in a death,</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">What cannot you and I perform upon</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">The unguarded Duncan? what not put upon</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">His spongy officers, who shall bear the guilt</a><br/>
<a NAME="79">Of our great quell?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="80">Bring forth men-children only;</a><br/>
<a NAME="81">For thy undaunted mettle should compose</a><br/>
<a NAME="82">Nothing but males. Will it not be received,</a><br/>
<a NAME="83">When we have mark'd with blood those sleepy two</a><br/>
<a NAME="84">Of his own chamber and used their very daggers,</a><br/>
<a NAME="85">That they have done't?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>LADY MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="86">Who dares receive it other,</a><br/>
<a NAME="87">As we shall make our griefs and clamour roar</a><br/>
<a NAME="88">Upon his death?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>MACBETH</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="89">                  I am settled, and bend up</a><br/>
<a NAME="90">Each corporal agent to this terrible feat.</a><br/>
<a NAME="91">Away, and mock the time with fairest show:</a><br/>
<a NAME="92">False face must hide what the false heart doth know.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
