<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE VI. Forres. The palace.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter LENNOX and another Lord</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>LENNOX</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">My former speeches have but hit your thoughts,</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">Which can interpret further: only, I say,</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">Things have been strangely borne. The</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">gracious Duncan</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Was pitied of Macbeth: marry, he was dead:</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">And the right-valiant Banquo walk'd too late;</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Whom, you may say, if't please you, Fleance kill'd,</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">For Fleance fled: men must not walk too late.</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Who cannot want the thought how monstrous</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">It was for Malcolm and for Donalbain</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">To kill their gracious father? damned fact!</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">How it did grieve Macbeth! did he not straight</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">In pious rage the two delinquents tear,</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">That were the slaves of drink and thralls of sleep?</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">Was not that nobly done? Ay, and wisely too;</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">For 'twould have anger'd any heart alive</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">To hear the men deny't. So that, I say,</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">He has borne all things well: and I do think</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">That had he Duncan's sons under his key--</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">As, an't please heaven, he shall not--they</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">should find</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">What 'twere to kill a father; so should Fleance.</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">But, peace! for from broad words and 'cause he fail'd</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">His presence at the tyrant's feast, I hear</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">Macduff lives in disgrace: sir, can you tell</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">Where he bestows himself?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="27">The son of Duncan,</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">From whom this tyrant holds the due of birth</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Lives in the English court, and is received</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Of the most pious Edward with such grace</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">That the malevolence of fortune nothing</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">Takes from his high respect: thither Macduff</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">Is gone to pray the holy king, upon his aid</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">To wake Northumberland and warlike Siward:</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">That, by the help of these--with Him above</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">To ratify the work--we may again</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">Give to our tables meat, sleep to our nights,</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">Free from our feasts and banquets bloody knives,</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">Do faithful homage and receive free honours:</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">All which we pine for now: and this report</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">Hath so exasperate the king that he</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">Prepares for some attempt of war.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>LENNOX</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="43">Sent he to Macduff?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="44">He did: and with an absolute 'Sir, not I,'</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">The cloudy messenger turns me his back,</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">And hums, as who should say 'You'll rue the time</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">That clogs me with this answer.'</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>LENNOX</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="48">And that well might</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">Advise him to a caution, to hold what distance</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">His wisdom can provide. Some holy angel</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">Fly to the court of England and unfold</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">His message ere he come, that a swift blessing</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">May soon return to this our suffering country</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">Under a hand accursed!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>Lord</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="55">I'll send my prayers with him.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
