<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE II. Another part of the island.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter CALIBAN with a burden of wood. A noise of thunder heard</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">All the infections that the sun sucks up</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">From bogs, fens, flats, on Prosper fall and make him</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">By inch-meal a disease! His spirits hear me</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">And yet I needs must curse. But they'll nor pinch,</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Fright me with urchin--shows, pitch me i' the mire,</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">Nor lead me, like a firebrand, in the dark</a><br/>
<a NAME="7">Out of my way, unless he bid 'em; but</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">For every trifle are they set upon me;</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">Sometime like apes that mow and chatter at me</a><br/>
<a NAME="10">And after bite me, then like hedgehogs which</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Lie tumbling in my barefoot way and mount</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">Their pricks at my footfall; sometime am I</a><br/>
<a NAME="13">All wound with adders who with cloven tongues</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">Do hiss me into madness.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter TRINCULO</i></p>
<a NAME="15">Lo, now, lo!</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">Here comes a spirit of his, and to torment me</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">For bringing wood in slowly. I'll fall flat;</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">Perchance he will not mind me.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="19">Here's neither bush nor shrub, to bear off</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">any weather at all, and another storm brewing;</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">I hear it sing i' the wind: yond same black</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">cloud, yond huge one, looks like a foul</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">bombard that would shed his liquor. If it</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">should thunder as it did before, I know not</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">where to hide my head: yond same cloud cannot</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">choose but fall by pailfuls. What have we</a><br/>
<a NAME="27">here? a man or a fish? dead or alive? A fish:</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">he smells like a fish; a very ancient and fish-</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">like smell; a kind of not of the newest Poor-</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">John. A strange fish! Were I in England now,</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">as once I was, and had but this fish painted,</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">not a holiday fool there but would give a piece</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">of silver: there would this monster make a</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">man; any strange beast there makes a man:</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">when they will not give a doit to relieve a lame</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">beggar, they will lazy out ten to see a dead</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">Indian. Legged like a man and his fins like</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">arms! Warm o' my troth! I do now let loose</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">my opinion; hold it no longer: this is no fish,</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">but an islander, that hath lately suffered by a</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">thunderbolt.</a><br/>
<p><i>Thunder</i></p>
<a NAME="42">Alas, the storm is come again! my best way is to</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">creep under his gaberdine; there is no other</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">shelter hereabouts: misery acquaints a man with</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">strange bed-fellows. I will here shroud till the</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">dregs of the storm be past.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter STEPHANO, singing: a bottle in his hand</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="47">   I shall no more to sea, to sea,</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">Here shall I die ashore--</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">This is a very scurvy tune to sing at a man's</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">funeral: well, here's my comfort.</a><br/>
<p><i>Drinks</i></p>
<p><i>Sings</i></p>
<a NAME="51">The master, the swabber, the boatswain and I,</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">The gunner and his mate</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">Loved Mall, Meg and Marian and Margery,</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">But none of us cared for Kate;</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">For she had a tongue with a tang,</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">Would cry to a sailor, Go hang!</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">She loved not the savour of tar nor of pitch,</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">Yet a tailor might scratch her where'er she did itch:</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">Then to sea, boys, and let her go hang!</a><br/>
<a NAME="60">This is a scurvy tune too: but here's my comfort.</a><br/>
<p><i>Drinks</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="61">Do not torment me: Oh!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="62">What's the matter? Have we devils here? Do you put</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">tricks upon's with savages and men of Ind, ha? I</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">have not scaped drowning to be afeard now of your</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">four legs; for it hath been said, As proper a man as</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">ever went on four legs cannot make him give ground;</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">and it shall be said so again while Stephano</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">breathes at's nostrils.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="69">The spirit torments me; Oh!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="70">This is some monster of the isle with four legs, who</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">hath got, as I take it, an ague. Where the devil</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">should he learn our language? I will give him some</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">relief, if it be but for that. if I can recover him</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">and keep him tame and get to Naples with him, he's a</a><br/>
<a NAME="75">present for any emperor that ever trod on neat's leather.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="76">Do not torment me, prithee; I'll bring my wood home faster.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="77">He's in his fit now and does not talk after the</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">wisest. He shall taste of my bottle: if he have</a><br/>
<a NAME="79">never drunk wine afore will go near to remove his</a><br/>
<a NAME="80">fit. If I can recover him and keep him tame, I will</a><br/>
<a NAME="81">not take too much for him; he shall pay for him that</a><br/>
<a NAME="82">hath him, and that soundly.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="83">Thou dost me yet but little hurt; thou wilt anon, I</a><br/>
<a NAME="84">know it by thy trembling: now Prosper works upon thee.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="85">Come on your ways; open your mouth; here is that</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">which will give language to you, cat: open your</a><br/>
<a NAME="87">mouth; this will shake your shaking, I can tell you,</a><br/>
<a NAME="88">and that soundly: you cannot tell who's your friend:</a><br/>
<a NAME="89">open your chaps again.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="90">I should know that voice: it should be--but he is</a><br/>
<a NAME="91">drowned; and these are devils: O defend me!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="92">Four legs and two voices: a most delicate monster!</a><br/>
<a NAME="93">His forward voice now is to speak well of his</a><br/>
<a NAME="94">friend; his backward voice is to utter foul speeches</a><br/>
<a NAME="95">and to detract. If all the wine in my bottle will</a><br/>
<a NAME="96">recover him, I will help his ague. Come. Amen! I</a><br/>
<a NAME="97">will pour some in thy other mouth.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="98">Stephano!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="99">Doth thy other mouth call me? Mercy, mercy! This is</a><br/>
<a NAME="100">a devil, and no monster: I will leave him; I have no</a><br/>
<a NAME="101">long spoon.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="102">Stephano! If thou beest Stephano, touch me and</a><br/>
<a NAME="103">speak to me: for I am Trinculo--be not afeard--thy</a><br/>
<a NAME="104">good friend Trinculo.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="105">If thou beest Trinculo, come forth: I'll pull thee</a><br/>
<a NAME="106">by the lesser legs: if any be Trinculo's legs,</a><br/>
<a NAME="107">these are they. Thou art very Trinculo indeed! How</a><br/>
<a NAME="108">camest thou to be the siege of this moon-calf? can</a><br/>
<a NAME="109">he vent Trinculos?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="110">I took him to be killed with a thunder-stroke. But</a><br/>
<a NAME="111">art thou not drowned, Stephano? I hope now thou art</a><br/>
<a NAME="112">not drowned. Is the storm overblown? I hid me</a><br/>
<a NAME="113">under the dead moon-calf's gaberdine for fear of</a><br/>
<a NAME="114">the storm. And art thou living, Stephano? O</a><br/>
<a NAME="115">Stephano, two Neapolitans 'scaped!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="116">Prithee, do not turn me about; my stomach is not constant.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="117">[Aside]  These be fine things, an if they be</a><br/>
<a NAME="118">not sprites.</a><br/>
<a NAME="119">That's a brave god and bears celestial liquor.</a><br/>
<a NAME="120">I will kneel to him.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="121">How didst thou 'scape? How camest thou hither?</a><br/>
<a NAME="122">swear by this bottle how thou camest hither. I</a><br/>
<a NAME="123">escaped upon a butt of sack which the sailors</a><br/>
<a NAME="124">heaved o'erboard, by this bottle; which I made of</a><br/>
<a NAME="125">the bark of a tree with mine own hands since I was</a><br/>
<a NAME="126">cast ashore.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="127">I'll swear upon that bottle to be thy true subject;</a><br/>
<a NAME="128">for the liquor is not earthly.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="129">Here; swear then how thou escapedst.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech24"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="130">Swum ashore. man, like a duck: I can swim like a</a><br/>
<a NAME="131">duck, I'll be sworn.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech25"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="132">Here, kiss the book. Though thou canst swim like a</a><br/>
<a NAME="133">duck, thou art made like a goose.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech26"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="134">O Stephano. hast any more of this?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech27"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="135">The whole butt, man: my cellar is in a rock by the</a><br/>
<a NAME="136">sea-side where my wine is hid. How now, moon-calf!</a><br/>
<a NAME="137">how does thine ague?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech28"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="138">Hast thou not dropp'd from heaven?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech29"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="139">Out o' the moon, I do assure thee: I was the man i'</a><br/>
<a NAME="140">the moon when time was.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech30"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="141">I have seen thee in her and I do adore thee:</a><br/>
<a NAME="142">My mistress show'd me thee and thy dog and thy bush.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech31"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="143">Come, swear to that; kiss the book: I will furnish</a><br/>
<a NAME="144">it anon with new contents swear.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech32"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="145">By this good light, this is a very shallow monster!</a><br/>
<a NAME="146">I afeard of him! A very weak monster! The man i'</a><br/>
<a NAME="147">the moon! A most poor credulous monster! Well</a><br/>
<a NAME="148">drawn, monster, in good sooth!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech33"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="149">I'll show thee every fertile inch o' th' island;</a><br/>
<a NAME="150">And I will kiss thy foot: I prithee, be my god.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech34"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="151">By this light, a most perfidious and drunken</a><br/>
<a NAME="152">monster! when 's god's asleep, he'll rob his bottle.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech35"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="153">I'll kiss thy foot; I'll swear myself thy subject.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech36"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="154">Come on then; down, and swear.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech37"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="155">I shall laugh myself to death at this puppy-headed</a><br/>
<a NAME="156">monster. A most scurvy monster! I could find in my</a><br/>
<a NAME="157">heart to beat him,--</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech38"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="158">Come, kiss.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech39"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="159">But that the poor monster's in drink: an abominable monster!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech40"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="160">I'll show thee the best springs; I'll pluck thee berries;</a><br/>
<a NAME="161">I'll fish for thee and get thee wood enough.</a><br/>
<a NAME="162">A plague upon the tyrant that I serve!</a><br/>
<a NAME="163">I'll bear him no more sticks, but follow thee,</a><br/>
<a NAME="164">Thou wondrous man.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech41"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="165">A most ridiculous monster, to make a wonder of a</a><br/>
<a NAME="166">Poor drunkard!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech42"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="167">I prithee, let me bring thee where crabs grow;</a><br/>
<a NAME="168">And I with my long nails will dig thee pignuts;</a><br/>
<a NAME="169">Show thee a jay's nest and instruct thee how</a><br/>
<a NAME="170">To snare the nimble marmoset; I'll bring thee</a><br/>
<a NAME="171">To clustering filberts and sometimes I'll get thee</a><br/>
<a NAME="172">Young scamels from the rock. Wilt thou go with me?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech43"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="173">I prithee now, lead the way without any more</a><br/>
<a NAME="174">talking. Trinculo, the king and all our company</a><br/>
<a NAME="175">else being drowned, we will inherit here: here;</a><br/>
<a NAME="176">bear my bottle: fellow Trinculo, we'll fill him by</a><br/>
<a NAME="177">and by again.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech44"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="178">[Sings drunkenly]</a><br/>
<a NAME="179">Farewell master; farewell, farewell!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech45"><b>TRINCULO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="180">A howling monster: a drunken monster!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech46"><b>CALIBAN</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="181">   No more dams I'll make for fish</a><br/>
<a NAME="182">Nor fetch in firing</a><br/>
<a NAME="183">At requiring;</a><br/>
<a NAME="184">Nor scrape trencher, nor wash dish</a><br/>
<a NAME="185">'Ban, 'Ban, Cacaliban</a><br/>
<a NAME="186">Has a new master: get a new man.</a><br/>
<a NAME="187">Freedom, hey-day! hey-day, freedom! freedom,</a><br/>
<a NAME="188">hey-day, freedom!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech47"><b>STEPHANO</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="189">O brave monster! Lead the way.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
