<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE I. Rome. A street.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Enter FLAVIUS, MARULLUS, and certain Commoners</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>FLAVIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Hence! home, you idle creatures get you home:</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">Is this a holiday? what! know you not,</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">Being mechanical, you ought not walk</a><br/>
<a NAME="4">Upon a labouring day without the sign</a><br/>
<a NAME="5">Of your profession? Speak, what trade art thou?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>First Commoner</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="6">Why, sir, a carpenter.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>MARULLUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="7">Where is thy leather apron and thy rule?</a><br/>
<a NAME="8">What dost thou with thy best apparel on?</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">You, sir, what trade are you?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>Second Commoner</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="10">Truly, sir, in respect of a fine workman, I am but,</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">as you would say, a cobbler.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>MARULLUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="12">But what trade art thou? answer me directly.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>Second Commoner</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="13">A trade, sir, that, I hope, I may use with a safe</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">conscience; which is, indeed, sir, a mender of bad soles.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>MARULLUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="15">What trade, thou knave? thou naughty knave, what trade?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>Second Commoner</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="16">Nay, I beseech you, sir, be not out with me: yet,</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">if you be out, sir, I can mend you.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>MARULLUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="18">What meanest thou by that? mend me, thou saucy fellow!</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>Second Commoner</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="19">Why, sir, cobble you.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>FLAVIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="20">Thou art a cobbler, art thou?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>Second Commoner</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="21">Truly, sir, all that I live by is with the awl: I</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">meddle with no tradesman's matters, nor women's</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">matters, but with awl. I am, indeed, sir, a surgeon</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">to old shoes; when they are in great danger, I</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">recover them. As proper men as ever trod upon</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">neat's leather have gone upon my handiwork.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>FLAVIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="27">But wherefore art not in thy shop today?</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">Why dost thou lead these men about the streets?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>Second Commoner</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="29">Truly, sir, to wear out their shoes, to get myself</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">into more work. But, indeed, sir, we make holiday,</a><br/>
<a NAME="31">to see Caesar and to rejoice in his triumph.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>MARULLUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="32">Wherefore rejoice? What conquest brings he home?</a><br/>
<a NAME="33">What tributaries follow him to Rome,</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">To grace in captive bonds his chariot-wheels?</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">You blocks, you stones, you worse than senseless things!</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">O you hard hearts, you cruel men of Rome,</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">Knew you not Pompey? Many a time and oft</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">Have you climb'd up to walls and battlements,</a><br/>
<a NAME="39">To towers and windows, yea, to chimney-tops,</a><br/>
<a NAME="40">Your infants in your arms, and there have sat</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">The livelong day, with patient expectation,</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">To see great Pompey pass the streets of Rome:</a><br/>
<a NAME="43">And when you saw his chariot but appear,</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">Have you not made an universal shout,</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">That Tiber trembled underneath her banks,</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">To hear the replication of your sounds</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">Made in her concave shores?</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">And do you now put on your best attire?</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">And do you now cull out a holiday?</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">And do you now strew flowers in his way</a><br/>
<a NAME="51">That comes in triumph over Pompey's blood? Be gone!</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">Run to your houses, fall upon your knees,</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">Pray to the gods to intermit the plague</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">That needs must light on this ingratitude.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>FLAVIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="55">Go, go, good countrymen, and, for this fault,</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">Assemble all the poor men of your sort;</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">Draw them to Tiber banks, and weep your tears</a><br/>
<a NAME="58">Into the channel, till the lowest stream</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">Do kiss the most exalted shores of all.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt all the Commoners</i></p>
<a NAME="60">See whether their basest metal be not moved;</a><br/>
<a NAME="61">They vanish tongue-tied in their guiltiness.</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">Go you down that way towards the Capitol;</a><br/>
<a NAME="63">This way will I disrobe the images,</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">If you do find them deck'd with ceremonies.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>MARULLUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="65">May we do so?</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">You know it is the feast of Lupercal.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>FLAVIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="67">It is no matter; let no images</a><br/>
<a NAME="68">Be hung with Caesar's trophies. I'll about,</a><br/>
<a NAME="69">And drive away the vulgar from the streets:</a><br/>
<a NAME="70">So do you too, where you perceive them thick.</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">These growing feathers pluck'd from Caesar's wing</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">Will make him fly an ordinary pitch,</a><br/>
<a NAME="73">Who else would soar above the view of men</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">And keep us all in servile fearfulness.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
