<html>
<body>
<h3>SCENE II. CAESAR's house.</h3>
<blockquote>
<i>Thunder and lightning. Enter CAESAR, in his night-gown</i>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech1"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="1">Nor heaven nor earth have been at peace to-night:</a><br/>
<a NAME="2">Thrice hath Calpurnia in her sleep cried out,</a><br/>
<a NAME="3">'Help, ho! they murder Caesar!' Who's within?</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter a Servant</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech2"><b>Servant</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="4">My lord?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech3"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="5">Go bid the priests do present sacrifice</a><br/>
<a NAME="6">And bring me their opinions of success.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech4"><b>Servant</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="7">I will, my lord.</a><br/>
<p><i>Exit</i></p>
<p><i>Enter CALPURNIA</i></p>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech5"><b>CALPURNIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="8">What mean you, Caesar? think you to walk forth?</a><br/>
<a NAME="9">You shall not stir out of your house to-day.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech6"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="10">Caesar shall forth: the things that threaten'd me</a><br/>
<a NAME="11">Ne'er look'd but on my back; when they shall see</a><br/>
<a NAME="12">The face of Caesar, they are vanished.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech7"><b>CALPURNIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="13">Caesar, I never stood on ceremonies,</a><br/>
<a NAME="14">Yet now they fright me. There is one within,</a><br/>
<a NAME="15">Besides the things that we have heard and seen,</a><br/>
<a NAME="16">Recounts most horrid sights seen by the watch.</a><br/>
<a NAME="17">A lioness hath whelped in the streets;</a><br/>
<a NAME="18">And graves have yawn'd, and yielded up their dead;</a><br/>
<a NAME="19">Fierce fiery warriors fought upon the clouds,</a><br/>
<a NAME="20">In ranks and squadrons and right form of war,</a><br/>
<a NAME="21">Which drizzled blood upon the Capitol;</a><br/>
<a NAME="22">The noise of battle hurtled in the air,</a><br/>
<a NAME="23">Horses did neigh, and dying men did groan,</a><br/>
<a NAME="24">And ghosts did shriek and squeal about the streets.</a><br/>
<a NAME="25">O Caesar! these things are beyond all use,</a><br/>
<a NAME="26">And I do fear them.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech8"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="27">What can be avoided</a><br/>
<a NAME="28">Whose end is purposed by the mighty gods?</a><br/>
<a NAME="29">Yet Caesar shall go forth; for these predictions</a><br/>
<a NAME="30">Are to the world in general as to Caesar.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech9"><b>CALPURNIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="31">When beggars die, there are no comets seen;</a><br/>
<a NAME="32">The heavens themselves blaze forth the death of princes.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech10"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="33">Cowards die many times before their deaths;</a><br/>
<a NAME="34">The valiant never taste of death but once.</a><br/>
<a NAME="35">Of all the wonders that I yet have heard.</a><br/>
<a NAME="36">It seems to me most strange that men should fear;</a><br/>
<a NAME="37">Seeing that death, a necessary end,</a><br/>
<a NAME="38">Will come when it will come.</a><br/>
<p><i>Re-enter Servant</i></p>
<a NAME="39">What say the augurers?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech11"><b>Servant</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="40">They would not have you to stir forth to-day.</a><br/>
<a NAME="41">Plucking the entrails of an offering forth,</a><br/>
<a NAME="42">They could not find a heart within the beast.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech12"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="43">The gods do this in shame of cowardice:</a><br/>
<a NAME="44">Caesar should be a beast without a heart,</a><br/>
<a NAME="45">If he should stay at home to-day for fear.</a><br/>
<a NAME="46">No, Caesar shall not: danger knows full well</a><br/>
<a NAME="47">That Caesar is more dangerous than he:</a><br/>
<a NAME="48">We are two lions litter'd in one day,</a><br/>
<a NAME="49">And I the elder and more terrible:</a><br/>
<a NAME="50">And Caesar shall go forth.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech13"><b>CALPURNIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="51">Alas, my lord,</a><br/>
<a NAME="52">Your wisdom is consumed in confidence.</a><br/>
<a NAME="53">Do not go forth to-day: call it my fear</a><br/>
<a NAME="54">That keeps you in the house, and not your own.</a><br/>
<a NAME="55">We'll send Mark Antony to the senate-house:</a><br/>
<a NAME="56">And he shall say you are not well to-day:</a><br/>
<a NAME="57">Let me, upon my knee, prevail in this.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech14"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="58">Mark Antony shall say I am not well,</a><br/>
<a NAME="59">And, for thy humour, I will stay at home.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter DECIUS BRUTUS</i></p>
<a NAME="60">Here's Decius Brutus, he shall tell them so.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech15"><b>DECIUS BRUTUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="61">Caesar, all hail! good morrow, worthy Caesar:</a><br/>
<a NAME="62">I come to fetch you to the senate-house.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech16"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="63">And you are come in very happy time,</a><br/>
<a NAME="64">To bear my greeting to the senators</a><br/>
<a NAME="65">And tell them that I will not come to-day:</a><br/>
<a NAME="66">Cannot, is false, and that I dare not, falser:</a><br/>
<a NAME="67">I will not come to-day: tell them so, Decius.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech17"><b>CALPURNIA</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="68">Say he is sick.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech18"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="69">                  Shall Caesar send a lie?</a><br/>
<a NAME="70">Have I in conquest stretch'd mine arm so far,</a><br/>
<a NAME="71">To be afraid to tell graybeards the truth?</a><br/>
<a NAME="72">Decius, go tell them Caesar will not come.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech19"><b>DECIUS BRUTUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="73">Most mighty Caesar, let me know some cause,</a><br/>
<a NAME="74">Lest I be laugh'd at when I tell them so.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech20"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="75">The cause is in my will: I will not come;</a><br/>
<a NAME="76">That is enough to satisfy the senate.</a><br/>
<a NAME="77">But for your private satisfaction,</a><br/>
<a NAME="78">Because I love you, I will let you know:</a><br/>
<a NAME="79">Calpurnia here, my wife, stays me at home:</a><br/>
<a NAME="80">She dreamt to-night she saw my statua,</a><br/>
<a NAME="81">Which, like a fountain with an hundred spouts,</a><br/>
<a NAME="82">Did run pure blood: and many lusty Romans</a><br/>
<a NAME="83">Came smiling, and did bathe their hands in it:</a><br/>
<a NAME="84">And these does she apply for warnings, and portents,</a><br/>
<a NAME="85">And evils imminent; and on her knee</a><br/>
<a NAME="86">Hath begg'd that I will stay at home to-day.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech21"><b>DECIUS BRUTUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="87">This dream is all amiss interpreted;</a><br/>
<a NAME="88">It was a vision fair and fortunate:</a><br/>
<a NAME="89">Your statue spouting blood in many pipes,</a><br/>
<a NAME="90">In which so many smiling Romans bathed,</a><br/>
<a NAME="91">Signifies that from you great Rome shall suck</a><br/>
<a NAME="92">Reviving blood, and that great men shall press</a><br/>
<a NAME="93">For tinctures, stains, relics and cognizance.</a><br/>
<a NAME="94">This by Calpurnia's dream is signified.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech22"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="95">And this way have you well expounded it.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech23"><b>DECIUS BRUTUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="96">I have, when you have heard what I can say:</a><br/>
<a NAME="97">And know it now: the senate have concluded</a><br/>
<a NAME="98">To give this day a crown to mighty Caesar.</a><br/>
<a NAME="99">If you shall send them word you will not come,</a><br/>
<a NAME="100">Their minds may change. Besides, it were a mock</a><br/>
<a NAME="101">Apt to be render'd, for some one to say</a><br/>
<a NAME="102">'Break up the senate till another time,</a><br/>
<a NAME="103">When Caesar's wife shall meet with better dreams.'</a><br/>
<a NAME="104">If Caesar hide himself, shall they not whisper</a><br/>
<a NAME="105">'Lo, Caesar is afraid'?</a><br/>
<a NAME="106">Pardon me, Caesar; for my dear dear love</a><br/>
<a NAME="107">To our proceeding bids me tell you this;</a><br/>
<a NAME="108">And reason to my love is liable.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech24"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="109">How foolish do your fears seem now, Calpurnia!</a><br/>
<a NAME="110">I am ashamed I did yield to them.</a><br/>
<a NAME="111">Give me my robe, for I will go.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter PUBLIUS, BRUTUS, LIGARIUS, METELLUS, CASCA, TREBONIUS, and CINNA</i></p>
<a NAME="112">And look where Publius is come to fetch me.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech25"><b>PUBLIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="113">Good morrow, Caesar.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech26"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="114">Welcome, Publius.</a><br/>
<a NAME="115">What, Brutus, are you stirr'd so early too?</a><br/>
<a NAME="116">Good morrow, Casca. Caius Ligarius,</a><br/>
<a NAME="117">Caesar was ne'er so much your enemy</a><br/>
<a NAME="118">As that same ague which hath made you lean.</a><br/>
<a NAME="119">What is 't o'clock?</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech27"><b>BRUTUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="120">Caesar, 'tis strucken eight.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech28"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="121">I thank you for your pains and courtesy.</a><br/>
<p><i>Enter ANTONY</i></p>
<a NAME="122">See! Antony, that revels long o' nights,</a><br/>
<a NAME="123">Is notwithstanding up. Good morrow, Antony.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech29"><b>ANTONY</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="124">So to most noble Caesar.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech30"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="125">Bid them prepare within:</a><br/>
<a NAME="126">I am to blame to be thus waited for.</a><br/>
<a NAME="127">Now, Cinna: now, Metellus: what, Trebonius!</a><br/>
<a NAME="128">I have an hour's talk in store for you;</a><br/>
<a NAME="129">Remember that you call on me to-day:</a><br/>
<a NAME="130">Be near me, that I may remember you.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech31"><b>TREBONIUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="131">Caesar, I will:</a><br/>
<p><i>Aside</i></p>
<a NAME="132">and so near will I be,</a><br/>
<a NAME="133">That your best friends shall wish I had been further.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech32"><b>CAESAR</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="134">Good friends, go in, and taste some wine with me;</a><br/>
<a NAME="135">And we, like friends, will straightway go together.</a><br/>
</blockquote>
<a NAME="speech33"><b>BRUTUS</b></a>
<blockquote>
<a NAME="136">[Aside]  That every like is not the same, O Caesar,</a><br/>
<a NAME="137">The heart of Brutus yearns to think upon!</a><br/>
<p><i>Exeunt</i></p>
</blockquote>
</body>
</html>
